<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a book called The Quakers catechism, put out by Richard Baxter. Wherein the slanderer is searched, his questions answered, and his deceit discovered, whereby the simple have been deceived: and the popery proved in his own bosom, which he would cast upon the Quakers. Published for the sake of all who desire to come out of Babylon, to the foundation of the true prophets and apostles, where Christ Iesus is the light and corner stone; where God is building a habitation of righteousness and everlasting peace; where the children of light do rest. Also some quæries for the discovering the false grounds of the literal preist-hood of these days, in the last times of antichrist. If you know the truth, the truth shall make you free. / Iames Nailor.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89824</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E851_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207416</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866466</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866466</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118741</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89824)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 129:E851[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a book called The Quakers catechism, put out by Richard Baxter. Wherein the slanderer is searched, his questions answered, and his deceit discovered, whereby the simple have been deceived: and the popery proved in his own bosom, which he would cast upon the Quakers. Published for the sake of all who desire to come out of Babylon, to the foundation of the true prophets and apostles, where Christ Iesus is the light and corner stone; where God is building a habitation of righteousness and everlasting peace; where the children of light do rest. Also some quæries for the discovering the false grounds of the literal preist-hood of these days, in the last times of antichrist. If you know the truth, the truth shall make you free. / Iames Nailor.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to Baxter, Richard.  The Quakers catechism, or, the Quakers questioned, their questions answered, and both published.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Quakers catechism.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118741:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A BOOK CALLED <hi>The Quakers Catechiſm,</hi> Put out by <hi>RICHARD BAXTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Slanderer is ſearched, his Queſtions Anſwered, and his Deceit diſcovered, whereby the Simple have been deceived: And the Popery proved in his own boſom, which he would caſt upon the Quakers.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the ſake of all who deſire to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to the Foundation of the true Prophets and Apoſtles, where Chriſt Ieſus is the Light and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Stone; where God is building a Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Righteouſneſs and everlaſting Peace; where the Children of Light do reſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome Quaeries for the diſcovering the falſe Grounds of the literal Prieſt-hood of theſe days, in the laſt times of Antichriſt.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>If you know the truth, the truth ſhall make you free.</hi> 
               <bibl>Iames Nailor.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118741:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118741:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A BOOK CALLED <hi>The Quakers Catechiſm.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>To thee</hi> Richard Baxter,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHo haſt bent thy Tongue againſt the Innocent, caſting out thy envious ſlanders againſt the Lamb, who is appeared againſt the oppreſſion and deceit of all ſorts of people, who have profeſſed his pure Name in words, but have not joyned to his life and Spirit; but are joyned to the worldly lovers, and ſtand in your own will, and the poor is oppreſſed by him that is too ſtrong for him; and with that proud Spirit art thou joyned, pleading its cauſe againſt the Lamb, who cannot bow to any unrighteouſneſs, and againſt him art thou fighting with the ſame weapons that ever thy Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed. Canſt thou behold, and not bluſh at the lies thou haſt muſtered up in this book againſt the truth? Is this the end of all thy profeſſion, that thou art become a bloody perſecuter? Is there no difference with thee now, between ſuffering for conſcience ſake, and burning a Thief in the hand? thou art he that ever numbered the Lamb amongſt tranſgreſſors; and what are we, that thou art ſet againſt a poor deſpiſed people, troden upon every where, at your wills and pleaſures? Will this be for your honor, to combine together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a people, which by thy own words are ſo contemptible? Is all your proud hye-flovvn ſpirits joyned againſt ſo low a people, that any one can trample under-foot? It's eaſily ſeen, there is ſomething in the bottom, of greater price then all that's viſible; elſe why ſhould you gather thus from all Quarters? truly this will not be for your peace, He againſt vvhom you are riſen will break you: to pieces, vvhat
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118741:3"/>
ever become of our perſons; and thou vvilt ſee the day, <hi>Rich: Baxter,</hi> vvhen thy deeds vvill come to remembrance, and thy ſlanders ſet in order, and thou ſhalt ſee to whom thou art an enemy, though novv thou be wilfully ignorant of him; Were there any jot of his fear left in thee, might thou not once look back, and ſee thy vvays to be ſuch as none of Chriſts Miniſters vvere ever found in? Doſt thou believe that ever thy vvorks muſt be proved, or that thy Kingdom of Sin muſt come to an end? muſt not thy Covenant of ſin be broken? though thou intend it for term of life, yet remember thy latter end: Was not ever the old Perſecuters as blinde as thou art, till vvrath vvas upon them from Heaven? muſt they accompt for it that do not viſit him in Priſon, and ſhall ſuch eſcape as caſt in Priſon? Will it avail thee then to ſay, thou knevv not that it vvas he? Is not this ſufficient ground for thee to ſuſpect thy vvay, ſeeing none of Chriſts vvas ever in it before? but remember novv thou art warned, while thou haſt time.</p>
            <p>Though ſtriving for maſter-hood, and vain jangling I abhor, yet for the truths ſake, and the ſeed that is ſcattered, I cannot be ſilent, but muſt reprove that lying Spirit that's gone out into the World, and hath got entrance, and hath hardened many vvho ſometimes vvere ſomewhat tender; but novv hath he brought them forth againſt the Lamb to battle, and he hath none like theſe for his deſign, being finely covered with words, but their Works finde them out: Bleſſed be God for ever.</p>
            <p>In vvhat thou vvrites to the Reader, in thy Book, thou ſays thou ſays thou ſuppoſes he vvill marvel thou troubles thy ſelf vvith ſo vvilde a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, as the people called Quakers are; or that thou writes theſe fevv haſty lines on ſuch an occaſion: but thou ſaiſt thou vvilt tell the cauſe, vvhich is, that they have ſent to thee five ſeveral Papers, one of them vvith theſe Quaeries vvhich thou Anſvvers; and others of them almoſt nothing but a bundle of filthy railing vvords, as Serpent, Liar, Deceiver, Childe of the Devil, curſed Hypocrite, dumb Dog.</p>
            <p>I ſay every rational man may well marvel that theſe words ſhould be ſo haſtily by thee called filthy railing words, who profeſſes thy ſelf a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Scripture thy rule; ſeeing there is not one of theſe words, but by the ſpirit of Jeſus Chriſt they have been uſed, to ſuch who are in that nature to whom they belong; and the ſame Spirit can do no other but uſe the ſame words, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, where ever any is found in that practice. Hadſt thou ſaid we had been railers, the ſin had not been ſo great; but to ſay thoſe words given forth by the holy Ghoſt, as is plain in Scripture, are filthy railing words: here thou calls the Spirit filthy and unclean: but if thou read, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 29, 30. there thou mayeſt read thy blaſphemy, and what generation thou art of, and what ſhall befal thee: Doſt thou profeſs thy ſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt, and ſays the Scriptures are the word, and calls the Language of them filthy railing words? That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe words belong to thee, and that thou art in the ſame Generation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118741:3"/>
againſt whom they were ſpoken, I ſhall manifeſt it from thine own mouth, and bring thine own Book to witneſs againſt thee, and leave them to any honeſt heart who ſhall read them both, to judge, if thou be not found in the ſame practice, and ſo guilty of the ſame reproof. I tell thee, the Scribes and Phariſees, and falſe Prophets, might have had more ſhew to have ſpoken thus of theſe words then thou haſt; for they had no Scripture that had them in; but thou profeſſes that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which declares of the words from whom they were ſpoken, and to what ſort of people, and art found in their works; and of ſuch Chriſt himſelf was judged to be beſides himſelf: and we are called a wilde Generation. So the ſervant is no better then his Lord: and the Scripture is fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt further, They choſe a day to come into your aſſembly, and fell a queſtioning the Preacher thine aſſiſtant, and becauſe he avoided diſputing with them and fled, therefore they called him the hireling that fleeth, and ſo confeſſed themſelves to be Wolves. I ſay that you are hirelings, is plain by your practice: and thou confeſſes he avoided to diſpute with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and fled, and was not this true? but though the hireling did flee, doth this prove them Wolves? or did they then confeſs themſelves to be Wolves? if they did not, then he that ſaith they did, is a Lyar: But ſaiſt thou, it ſeems they referred it to <hi>John</hi> 10. 12. I ſay that place, though it declare you to be hirelings, yet doth it not declare all to be Wolves that come to diſpute with you, unleſs they be found guilty of devouring the people, as you are found guilty, in preaching for hire. But that they choſe out a day when thou ſhould be abſent, is falſe: for the Spirit of the Lord, by which we are guided, regards neither perſon nor places; but though they miſt thee then, did not they meet with thee at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> even in the high place where thou was preaching, and there demanded of thee, How the Miniſters of Chriſt, and the Miniſters of Antichriſt might be known? but could get nothing from thee, more then from thine aſſiſtant, unleſs ſuch words as theſe, people regard him not; and words ſtirring up the people to hale them out: which being readily executed by thy hearers, prevented the hirelings fleeing; but <hi>Tho: Good air</hi> ſtaying till thou had done, and then ſpeaking to thee and the people, all the ſatisfaction he got, was, that he was haled to priſon; yea twice hath he been impriſoned by thy Miniſtery: Oh ſhame with thy Epiſtle and thy Book, may not the Reader read thee a diſſembler, who ſays they choſe a time when thou was confined to thy chamber? thou mayſt well call theſe [haſty lines] for hadſt thou taken counſel at wiſdom, thou hadſt not thus manifeſted thy folly.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt they would not ſuffer thee to anſwer them peaceably in their Aſſembly without diſturbance; I ſay, had not this been a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time for thee to have proved thy Miniſtery, and to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved gainſayers? and had not thy hearers been as able to have kept thee from the diſturbance of one man, as to have haled him out of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118741:4"/>
doors? is not he blinde who ſees not thee through this cover? Art not thou aſhamed to ſay, that we are the children of darkneſs, and will not bring our deeds to the light, in this particular, as thou doſt in thy third pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? Couldſt thou have had a better opportunity then before ſo many people, and thou in thy high place, where none could diſturb thee? but in theſe excuſes thou layeſt but open thy own ſhame, as in the reſt of thy book: To ſend a man to priſon for ſpeaking to thee before thy Congregation, and then accuſe them, that they will not come to the light.</p>
            <p>But ſaiſt thou, I would have anſwered them in their Aſſembly: but why not in thine own? if the things had been profitable, might they not have been ſerviceable to them as well as to the other? but above all things, you cannot indure to be laid open before your hearers: You have led ſo many blinde, and there have kept them, that if ever they come to ſee your deeds laid open, you know you will loſe them, ſo that your beſt defence is to keep truth and light out of doors with clubs and halberts, and ſo to preſerve your deeds of darkneſs undiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered: and if any of your hearers begin to look towards the day, or light of Chriſt, and finde ſomething in their conſcience bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt their ſin and wickedneſs, of all other things you are moſt afraid, leſt by that they ſhould be guided; ſhewing your ſelves to be thoſe builders who moſt refuſe the corner ſtone, the light of the world; and of all things that ever were preached; you bid ſtand afar off from this, as the greateſt error. And whereas thou would make people believe, that we would not ſuffer you to come to our meeting; did not <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> in one Letter charge thee and Prieſt <hi>Oſland,</hi> to come to a meeting which was appointed at <hi>Chadwitch,</hi> in anſwer to your own Letters? which meeting was appointed and kept, and many people of ſeveral judgements came into the meeting with expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but neither thou nor Prieſt <hi>Oſland</hi> appeared, though you had ſent your boaſting Letters for a challenge about the ſame; ſuch as thou, no wonder, though thou preach down the light, and plead a continuance in ſin; whileſt thou lives, who makes no more uſe of the light in thy conſcience, in thy writings and actions.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaiſt, they charged thee in the name of the moſt high God to anſwer their Queſtions in writing, that they might Print them with their reply.</p>
            <p>And (ſaiſt thou) if I wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te to them they will print it, therefore thou choſedſt rather to print thine own papers, how mean ſoever, then let them do it.</p>
            <p>I ſay, how doth thy ſpeech bewray thee, who whileſt thou art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing us for not bringing our deeds to the light; thou confeſſes our publiſhing things, hath put thee upon Printing: and are they to be blamed for charging thee to anſwer their Queſtions in writing, who would neither come to their meeting, nor ſuffer them to ſpeak at thine, but ſent them to Priſon; and calls it no more perſecution, then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118741:4"/>
to burn a Thief in the hand; but though they charged thee to anſwer either in writing or printing; yet another Principle guides thee in ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering theſe falſhoods: that they charged thee not.</p>
            <p>Two Objections, thou ſaiſt that thou ſees, will be raiſed againſt thee; o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is, that the perſons are ſo contemptible, and the errors ſo groſs, that it is a needleſs work to ſtrive againſt them: To which thou an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, that our multiplying where we come, and the ſalvation of poor Chriſtians makes the neceſſity.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay: What Generation thou art of, who holds the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of any contemptible, is eaſily judged by any who have that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which reſpects no mans perſon, but from that Spirit you are groſly erred: And for our multiplying, that muſt increaſe to thy torment, and all <hi>Babylons</hi> Merchants; for God is multiplying his ſeed as the Stars of Heaven, though <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> be gathered againſt it, yet to the brightneſs of his riſing ſhall the Nations come, and the deſire is kindling now after the ſhakings, <hi>Iſa. 6. 3. Hag.</hi> 2. 7. and the Lamb hath ſet up his ſtandard, whereat all the beaſts of the field rage; yet he will take the victory; and for thy ſalvation thou tells on, what doſt thou intend to ſave them from, who art preaching up ſin as long as they live?</p>
            <p>And again thou ſaiſt, Its but the Churches of the Separatiſts and Anabaptiſts, that are emptied by theſe Seducers, and its beſt to let them alone to keep their own flocks.</p>
            <p>I ſay, Some of your Churches are ſo emptied, that you have few left to hear you, but prophane perſons, ſwearers, oppreſſors, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards and fighters, ſuch as beat in your ſynagogue, and theſe are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your prime hearers: but canſt thou not ſee thy confuſion, who in thy laſt was ſaying, We multiply where we come, and now Its but the Churches of the Separatiſts and Anabaptiſts: then, why cries thou out of ſo much danger? doth not thy ſpeech bewray thee? but ſaiſt thou, Here and there one of the unſetled ſort, or that had no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, inclines to them.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, one day ſhall thoſe whom you have moſt ſetled in your deceit, have moſt cauſe to curſe you, when they ſhall ſee them come from far, and ſit down in the Kingdom, and themſelves caſt out.</p>
            <p>Saiſt thou, I had far rather they had continued Separatiſts and Anabaptiſts, then turn Quakers; therefore wouldſt do all thou canſt to hinder.</p>
            <p>I ſay, thy Generation of Prieſts was ever haters of the greateſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of truth, and that we can witneſs. When we were of thoſe Churches, we were hated by you; when we walked as near as we could to the Letter, though the life we knew not, but now you have ceaſed your envy againſt all them; and againſt the Life and Light of Chriſt in us, is your greateſt envy.</p>
            <p>And ſaiſt thou, Its better to ſtop them where there's ſome hope of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118741:5"/>
Salvation, then let them run to perdition.</p>
            <p>I ſay, thou haſt undertaken two ways to ſtop us, one is with lies and ſlanders, which thy Book is full of; and another way taken with thee and thy Generation, is to get us ſtopt into Dungeons and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſtrait watch ſet, that none come to us, nor that we may have liberty to write nor ſpeak to any. But the latter of theſe is hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by you for the better weapon, yet both to no purpoſe, further then to prove our patience and obedience in Jeſus; and yourſelves of your Father, and in his works acting, that by them ye may be known, and we alſo.</p>
            <p>But ſays thou, I choſe rather to tell the world of theſe paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, then leave them to their reports, eſpecially hearing how they increaſe in <hi>London,</hi> and other parts; and that the ignorant have need of ſome plain information<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to prevent their Apoſtacy and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in this temptation.</p>
            <p>I ſay, they are ignorant indeed that needs thy information: and what thou telleſt, is moſt ſuitable to the world to be believed; for all who owns that light that leads out of the world, or where that ey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is open that leads out of the world, thy falſe information is judged and prevented, thy perdition and thy temptation; and with that Light that ſees thee and thy deceit, ſhall we grow both in <hi>London,</hi> and other parts, and thy refuge of lies be ſwept away.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118741:5"/>
               <p>AS to thy Paper to the Separatiſts and Anabaptiſts (as thou calls them) I deſire not to be buſie in other mens matters; onely this, whereas thou caſts it on the ſeparated people, to be nurſeries of impiety, and Infidels: I ſay, thou doſt but here mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thy ſhameleſs Spirit, who matters not what thou ſayeſt of others, ſo thou may but ſeek thy own praiſe; for all that know any thing of the fear of God, knows, that moſt of thoſe people have ſeparated from you pariſh Teachers, upon this very account (to wit) your infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and impiety: and if any amongſt them turn ſo groſly filthy, that they cannot keep them amongſt them, left it ſhould ſhame their Religion; yet theſe return to you, who forthwith receive them, and boaſt of them as rare Converts; nay, none ſo bad in their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but if they have but either Pig or Gooſe, or ought to be got towards hire, they are yours, and you are their maſters; ſuch as no one Sort of people in the Nation will joyn with, but onely you, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Teachers.</p>
               <p>But it ſeems thou haſt loſt ſome of thine alſo, as well as the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts; and thou prints a Letter, thou ſaiſt, thou ſent to one of them to reclaim him, under pretence that he deſired thy thoughts of us; and thy evil thoughts thou returns him in this Letter.</p>
               <p>And thou ſays, He was a yong and unſetled one; yet tells how much pains he had taken in duty, how much zeal he had profeſſed for God: And that he by ſo great a work of grace was converted from prophaneneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thus with thine own ſhame thou goes about to cover thee, having boaſted afore, as though none followed us but ſeparated people, or ſuch as had no Religion, or ever was accounted ſo to be. And thou goes on to ſhew him that he muſt needs be fallen from grace, becauſe he is fallen from your Miniſtry, and thy Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are ſuch as theſe. Are not we thoſe Miniſters, and in thoſe Ordinances you deſpiſed before Converſion?</p>
               <p>I ſay, The greateſt Papiſt in the world, having begot a Proſelyte, if he turn away from him, may as well uſe that Argument as thou, if falling from any ſuch form, or perſon be the error; but thou ſhould have firſt proved thy ſelf a Miniſter of Chriſt in thy life, and thy worſhip as he appointed it, and not changed in matter or manner, then hadſt thou ſaid ſomewhat to the purpoſe, elſe, its no error to deny the hireling, and his falſe worſhip, and turn to the light of Chriſt, by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118741:6"/>
it to be guided by all deceits. And ſays thou, Alaſs! that ever a man in his wits, ſhould no better know the work of Chriſt from Satans, nor know, that it is the Dragon whoſe warfare theſe men do manage. I ſay, Thou ſhameleſs one, doſt thou cauſe the ſervants of the living God to be hailed to priſon, and ſuffer them almoſt to be murthered before thy face, not at all reſiſting, but the people by thee ſtirred up to the thing, and for no other thing, but coming to declare to thy face againſt thy falſe worſhip, which God ever ſent his ſervants to do. And faiſt thou, We manage the war of the Dragon, and do the work of Satan: Is not the war of the Dragon, to devour the Lamb where he is manifeſt? which ever was the work the hirelings was found in; and is it not the Devil that caſts into Priſon the innocent, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. and was ever any under the Goſpel found in that work; but ſuch who was of the ſynagogue of Satan, though they called themſelves Jews, as you call your ſelves Chriſtians, but in the ſame nature and deeds: And do we manage the Dragons war, who ſuffer all this at your hands, and much more? prove that in Scriptures, or be aſhamed of thy falſe accuſation, and take it to thy ſelf, till thy rage ceaſe, and thou give over devouring the Lambs: Such never take pains with mens ſouls, who takes care, and lays ſnares to deſtroy their bodies: Chriſts ſheep was never ſuch wolves, by their fruits we know them; they who believe theſe to be Chriſts Miniſters, may ſoon believe the Devil is God (as thou ſaiſt) who would be worſhipped and obeyed in you.</p>
               <p>Thou further goes on, and tells him, whence this error comes, even from Helliſh pride; and to prove this, thou tells him, Where we have ſpent one hour, thou haſt ſpent an hundred in ſtudy and meditation, and prays to God for his Spirit of truth and grace, and that thy Prayers is as earneſt as ours, and thy life is much more holy and heavenly then ours, and therefore God is as it were more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to thee, to make known his truth to thee, then to us; and is not this apparent pride for us to be ſo confident, that we are wiſe and beloved in the eyes of God; and, that we run about with the ſhels on our head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in compariſon of thee.</p>
               <p>I ſay, the helliſh pride thou haſt plainly diſcovered, where it is. But whoſe righteouſneſs is all this by which thou haſt thus ingaged God to thee, who art but yet praying for the Spirit of truth and grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will God be ingaged with thy graceleſs lying ſpirit, which thou uſes in this thy Book, wherein thou utters ſo many graceleſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths, to ingage the world to thee? thou art miſtaken, God will not be ſo ingaged, nor with that Spirit; he will be ſerved with his own. Thy earneſt prayers and righteouſneſs, before the Spirit of truth and grace, and without it; how they ingage God, thou mayeſt read in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18. from the 16. to the 30. and <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 11, 12. and there thou may read thy boaſting lines, and their acceptance, and thy ingagements, and thy name; We know, God freely gives a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118741:6"/>
of his Spirit to every one of us, freely to profit withal; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving that to his praiſe, we receive more freely; and we are ſo far from ingagement of God by all we do, that we finde our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants, but this thou knoweſt not with thy va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n light words, who tells of our running away with the ſhell on our head: Our head thou knows not, who muſt break thee to pieces with all thy light boaſting vain words: Thou tells of <hi>Paul</hi> forewarning <hi>Timothy</hi> to ordain none who was a novice, leſt he ſhould be lifted up with pride, and ſo fall into the condemnation of the Devil; then thou mayeſt take this back a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain, and apply it, and therein read thy ſelf, and thy end in whom the pride is ſound, and not in the Quakers, and they are blinde who cannot ſee it: And tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaiſt, Pride is the maſter ſin of the Quakers, and thou proves it, becauſe that we go in a poor garb, and cry our-againſt pride, as if we were ſent from Heaven to perſwade men to wear no lace, cuffs or points, and to damn ſo many Miniſters for being called Maſter: But ſaiſt thou, ſpiritual pride is the moſt killing, and ſo goes on railing againſt us for theſe things, calling that ſpirit in ſcorn, An excellent Spirit, that can trample on all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glory: I ſay, Blaſphemer, thou ſhalt know when thou haſt finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy rage, that thou haſt ſpoken againſt the holy Spirit of God, ſent from Heaven, which both in Chriſt and his Apoſtles did perſwade againſt, and condemn ſuch things, which thou by the ſpirit of the Devil would uphold, and doſt plead for; and thou ſets down four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, wherein thou wilt prove our language of Hell, and the Devil ſpeaking by our mouthes, and the firſt is, They affirm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves perfect without ſin; and this thou ſaiſt is unpoſſible, and they are mad that believe it: I ſay, That we affirm ſelf-perfection, is but thy lying ſlander; or that we ſay we are Chriſt or God, as thou ſaiſt we do, but that we witneſs perfection from ſin, ſo far as we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Chriſt, we own it as Gods commands and guift, the end of Chriſts coming, and of giving forth his Miniſtery; as theſe Scriptures may witneſs, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 48. <hi>James</hi> 1. 17. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11, 12. 13. And, that it was the work of the Miniſtery whereunto they labor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, read <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 28, 29. and thou that Miniſters againſt this, and calls it the Language of Hell, and the Devils mouth, which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures witneſs, art a Blaſphemer and a Miniſter of Antichriſt, and its no railing to judge the tree by its fruit; and when thou haſt done, Thou ſaiſt, the Devil himſelf hath leſs pride then to think himſelf perfect without ſin; and if we have no ſin, what need we pray, or what need have we of the blood of Chriſt? I ſay, Thy confuſion is manifeſt, who before accuſed us that the Devil ſpake this in our mouthes, and now thou art clearing him of it; but what haſt thou to do, or he either, with perfection, who art out of Chriſt, and in your own wills, worldly-pleaſing, and envious, murtherers, in rage; what perfection is there, unleſs perfect wickedneſs? neither doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection exclude praying and the blood of Chriſt, for in his blood and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118741:7"/>
prayer it is wrought, and we kept.</p>
               <p>Thy ſecond thing is, That we ſet up our ſelves above all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God on earth, that we vilifie the moſt holy and eminent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, and condemn all the Churches of the World. To which I ſhall ſay no more but this, That theſe are three of thy lies rancked up together, leſt thou ſhould fail.</p>
               <p>Thy third thing is, That we damn all the people of God for 1600. years at leaſt: I ſay, This may well be matter of offence to thee, to deny all thy Generation ſince the Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to this day: therefore thou call'ſt it unmatchable pride; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or thoſe whom you have tortured<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> martyred and burned, whipt and impriſoned, to this day, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for conſcience ſake, follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the Lamb in their meaſure, them we own, and with them we ſuffer; though thou ſay, God had never ſuch a people on earth of theſe mens ways, yet was this the Church of Chriſt, whereof he was the head, and is the head, and there it was viſible, and there it is to all who are not blinde; but none of theſe pleaded for honorable Titles, as thou doſt, nor none ever did that believed; ſuch was ever out of the faith, read <hi>James</hi> 2. to the 10, <hi>verſe, John</hi> 5. 4. and 44. and if theſe be the few Hereticks (thou tells on) that thou ſays were our Predeceſſors of old: I ſay, We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but own theſe in their meaſure, though we go under the name of Hereticks with them, by the ſame Generation.</p>
               <p>Thy fourth thing is, That which thou calleſt our proud, ſcornful, railing Language, which thou ſaiſt ſhould put it out of doubt what ſpirit we are of, to any who are acquainted with Chriſts Spirit, and of Satan, and are able to judge of Spirits, and know darkneſs from light. I ſay, The Language of Chriſt we uſe to thee, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t found in the work of Satan, therefore thou canſt not bear it; but thy filthy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nclean words thou haſt caſt upon us in thy Book, which none in Scripture ever uſed, we ſhall leave to the judgement of Him that judges Spirits, and to all who know light from darkneſs: But thou fore-ſeeing thy ſelf guilty, makes an Objection; It is Scripture Language which they ſpeak, and when thou haſt done deceitfully, anſwereſt, ſaying, The greater your preſumptious ſin in making ſo ill an uſe of Scripture Language, and calls it, ſerving Satan; and thus thou proves i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaying, What if Chriſt called <hi>Judas</hi> a Devil, is it therefore lawful to call <hi>Peter</hi> ſo: I ſay, yea, If <hi>Peter</hi> be found in the Devils work, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 23. much more thou and thy Generation, who none of you yet came ſo far as <hi>Peter,</hi> who denyed all to follow Chriſt; but you will have all you can get, though you deny Chriſt, and all his Rules, for the getting of it; and ſuch are no faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, but of their own bellies, and their luſts and pride; as thou goeſt on ſtill pleading for thy maſterhood, ſaying, Alaſs, that a Chriſtian ſhould be ſo ignorant, as not to know that your being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Maſter, and Lord too, is commonly allowed in the Scripture; and that it is not the Title, but the Lording over mens faith, that is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118741:7"/>
I ſay, All thoſe that know any thing of the Faith of Chriſt, ſees you to be guilty of both, but will give you neither; which ſaith leads out of reſpect of perſons, and to ſerve a better maſter, then he that bears rule by his means: And thou tells thy thoughts of us (ſaiſt thou) it was the main advantage that the Reformers had for the ruine of the Papal Kingdom, to perſwade men that the Pope was Antichriſt; and to diſgrace the Popiſh Clergy, and ſays thou, They would attempt the deſtruction of our Church by the ſame means: I ſay, Why not? why may not that which lopt off ſome of your b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, now the time is come, cut up the whole root, being laid to it by the ſame power, in a great meaſure? Thou ſaiſt, Our firſt way is to bring people in diſlike with their Teachers, without which, we have no hope of ſucceeding: I ſay, Why not? you being of thoſe who ever ſhut up the Kingdom, therefore Chriſt, his Prophets and Apoſtles, did ever moſt cry out againſt the falſe Prophets, blinde Guides and Hirelings, who in all ages withſtood him, coming to his Kingdom, as you do now with the ſame weapons in this Generation; and Chriſts way is not changed, ſo the ſame wo againſt you is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, which you muſt inherit. And whereas thou ſaiſt, That the Papiſts have begotten this preſent Sect of Quakers: I ſay, The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is not divided againſt himſelf: had we been begot by the Papiſts, we ſhould have had more favor from you, who are come of that Line, as having hopes of us to have been reſtored to your former Kingdom, which ever ſtood ſo much in multitudes of people, that you might be Lords and Maſters over them: And thou ſays, We have here and there a Papiſt, lurking to be the chief Speaker amongſt us: I ſay, here thou doſt but manifeſt thy envy and deceit, to us and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; if thou know ſuch amongſt us, and do not produce it, then art thou deceitful to the truſt of the Nation; but if thou know none, then art thou a falſe accuſer, and out of thy own mouth art thou judged, who ſays we are heade<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with diſſembling Fryars; and this thou would make people believe with adding lies, ſaying that we ſay, the Pope is not Antichriſt, that we undermine the Scriptures, decry the Miniſtery, unchurch Churches, ſlight Juſtification by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs, draw men to admire our adherent Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſet up ſtrength of mans free-will, the exalting of Monaſtical Community and Virginity, and Alienation from worldly Imployment; All this, ſaiſt thou, the Papiſts hath taught the Quakers, ſo thou makes them up ten Lies together: And inſtead of proving us head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Fryars, thou haſt proved the Devil thy head, and father; for we confeſs the Pope to be Antichriſt, and all your Popiſh Clergy of his Linage, and with the Scriptures we ſo prove it; which Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures we own, with the true Miniſtery and Churches, Juſtification by Chriſts Righteouſneſs, freely put and given to us; whereby our own Righteouſneſs we deny, and ſet up the light within us, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Revelations, which the hirelings know not, therefore not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118741:8"/>
and we witneſs a judge above Scripture, and before Scripture, which we will not change for the Pope and all his Clergy, which we extol, and do not abſtain from worldly Imployments further, then by the Lord we are called, whom we preſer before all the world, which is our perfection and freedom from ſin in this life, which none of the Popiſh Clergy can teach us, though you may talk on it; but onely the Spirit of God, which we witneſs, which the Devil and the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings never befriended.</p>
               <p>Thou makes another Objection, That they hold out many certain truths, and cry down pride and drunkenneſs, and worldlineſs, and cry up mortification, charity and humility: And in thy Anſwer, thou ſaiſt, So do you as well, and better then we can do; it is common amongſt you, and thou hopes a little better maintained: Theſe you ſay are Points where you agree with the Papiſts; I ſay, much like, and to the ſame effect, but ſee how it is maintained in your practice; thy crying up humility, is ſeen in this thy boaſting, who ſays, Thy teaching is better then we can do; were it the gift of God, thou would ſee it to be free, and he not limited (by thy cannot) but free to give it to whom he pleaſeth, without reſpect of perſons. And for thy charity which thou cries up, is that it, by which <hi>Thomas Goodair</hi> was carryed twice to Priſon, for coming into the Idol Temple; if that be it, its preached through the Nation, thou might have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved labour of Printing it; not many of thy Brethren, but they have acted it: And if thy mortification ſtands in Cuffs and Ribonds, Lace and Points, being called Lord and Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryed, but thou haſt cryed it up in thy Book, and that very ſtrongly: And for your crying down pride, drunkenneſs, and worldlineſs, let your Kirks and Markets witneſs for you or againſt you, the effect of your crying, and fruits of your Miniſtery, which have all bent your ſelves in your Pulpits, to Preach up ſin for term of Life in your ſelves and your hearers; and here, thy crying up Cuffs and Points, and ſuch like ſtuffs.</p>
               <p>And thou bringeſt againſt us the Teſtimony of a Fryar, whom thou calls Maſter <hi>Coppenger,</hi> thou ſaiſt, of the Franciſcan order; I ſay, by the Maſterſhip thou giveſt him; he is one of thy Order, whereby you are both diſtinguiſhed, by the words of Chriſt to be none of his Miniſters, and ſo fitteſt for your purpoſe; and if reaſon may judge, moſt likely came over to ſecond your envy, againſt thoſe you call Quakers; elſe why did not you keep him, ſeeing the Law required it, then might it have been proved if he had been a Speaker amongſt us; but you ſhew your ſelves and your envy in this thing, as in many other, who would force the Teſtimony of a condemned perſon, and he not preſent, nor no two ever ſee him, by thy own confeſſion, in thy Paper; and yet this you Print ſo often over, thereby to deprive thouſands of their liberty in the ſervice of God, who are faithful, and have made proof of it, having thereto been called, againſt the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118741:8"/>
Popiſh Clergy and Biſhops; and the Powers they ſtirred up, as the Nation can witneſs; and if you were numbered from the firſt to the laſt, with your ſecret actings againſt us, there's not many of you in the Nation would be found clear of it; though now you be ſtirring up theſe Powers againſt the peaceable people, as you did the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, as a Generation never well, but when you are in miſchief; but our defence is the ſame againſt you, who will accompliſh his own work, and ſet his King upon his hill, notwithſtanding your Helliſh rage.</p>
               <p>Thou goes on telling, if any further ask thee, why the Papiſts are ſo diligent in thoſe works; and thou ſets down many hopes we have to accompliſh great things, which words are not worth taking up after thee: But to them all, I ſhall ſay this, Whoſoever hath but heard of the Blood that hath been ſhed, and the violence done to the Innocent by your Fore-fathers, the Popiſh Clergy, before they was denyed in the Nation; alſo what Blood hath been ſhed, and miſery undergone, to bring down your power ſet up in the Presbytery in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> the two laſt of theſe, which we can witneſs by ſad experience: I ſay, here's ſmall hopes for any that either loves God, or their ſouls or bodies either, or the Peace of the Nation, to labour in bringing forth ſuch a birth of Vipers; nay, we rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, to ſee the work begun thus far in the Nation, whereby he will rid us of the reſt of that brood, and their burthens, which is the greateſt oppreſſion that remains in the Nation, though this muſt be done with ſuffering, as the other was done with acting; the Lord having drawn forth many to that purpoſe, againſt whom you are gathered, as the ſand for multitude, yet are we not diſmayed, though beſet on every ſide, yet not deſtroyed, for we know him in whom we have believed.</p>
               <p>And thou ſaiſt, Conſider well of that Scripture <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 12, 13, 14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where Chriſt gave Miniſters for edification, unity, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Body; amongſt which thou haſt thruſt in thy curſed addition, ſaying (at laſt) the perfecting of the body: I ſay, When muſt that laſt be, ſeeing thou haſt denyed any perfection whileſt any lives in this world; it ſeems thou dreams your Miniſtery muſt laſt in another world, elſe how muſt you perfect them by your Miniſtery; or ſhall death do that which cannot be done, while they are living? So we have conſidered of that Scripture, and finde you to be none of thoſe Miniſters whom Chriſt gave, nor Miniſtring for that end, but againſt it, and ſo Miniſters of Antichriſt, blaſpheming the work of God; who call his power, at which all fleſh ſhall tremble, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Devil: And ſaiſt thou, If you turn to the Quakers, we ſhall know that you were before an unſetled Novice; and thou brings that of 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 19. they went out from us, but they were not of us: I ſay, What haſt thou to do with theſe words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>John</hi> was no hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor Perſecuter as thou art: thou art one of thoſe which <hi>John</hi> forewarns of, who abides not in the Doctrine of Chriſt; and all that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118741:9"/>
owns <hi>John,</hi> or his Epiſtle, muſt keep thee out of their Houſes, and have nought to do with thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if thou read his ſecond Epiſtle, 9, 10, 11 <hi>verſes,</hi> there thou may read thy ſelf caſt out by <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtery, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s few that comes from thee, need to look for ought but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, for then the hope of thy gain is loſt, further then thou takes by force: And thou falls a praying the Lord to open his eyes, and acquaint him with his great darkneſs and imperfection: I ſay, what eye is that which thou would have opened, ſince thou denies the Light within: Is the man blinde of his bodily eyes, and to what end ſhould he ſee his imperfection, ſeeing that thou denys that ever perfection can be attained to? Thy Prayers are an abomination, and they are blinde indeed, that ſtands in need of ſuch a Teacher, and knows no better ſpirit to pray with.</p>
               <p>Then thou makes an Oration, before thou Anſwers the Quaeries, wherein thou tells of ſeveral Papers, which thou received from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al perſons; as one <hi>Jane Hicks, Tho: Chandler,</hi> and <hi>Edward Newway, Richard Farnworth,</hi> and <hi>Tho: Goodair;</hi> but not being acquainted in the buſineſs, and ſeeing nothing herein of moment, but what is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in other places; I ſhall leave it till more knowledge of the thing.</p>
               <p>Then thou goes making a ſhow, as that thou would Anſwer our Quaeries, and theſe thou folds up by ſix together, which thou canſt not anſwer; and ſends us to a Book, we know not where, to ſeek an Anſwer, which thou calls a Defence of a Petition; yet though thou Anſwer not one of the ſix, in what thou falls ſhort in Anſwering, thou makes up in asking; asking ten, where thou anſwereſt not one: ſo that inſtead of anſwering 24. thou haſt asked above threeſcore; but few of thoſe thou waſt asked, haſt thou gone about to Anſwer: but thou begins, as followeth, with our firſt Quaery, and thy falſe ſlanders and lies thou caſts upon us, are double to thy Quaeries, as I ſhall make it appear, if I be called to number them; but I am weary with raking in that filthy puddle, yet thy Queries are anſwered, and ſome of thy lies diſproved.</p>
               <div type="errata">
                  <p>In page 43. line 12. for the Letter, read Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118741:9"/>
               <p>OUr 1. Query is, Whats the firſt Principle of pure Religion? Thy anſwer is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That God is, and ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, that he is a rewarder of them that dil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gently ſeek him; and thou queries the ground of our asking.</p>
               <p>I ſay the ground of our asking is, that the folly of ſuch Teachers as know net God and his way, may be made manifeſt, as it is by thy Anſwer; for the knowledge of what God is, is the ſubſtance, ground, and end of all pure Religion: which admits of no ſecond; for it is life eternal. But if thou ſay thou means believing, there is a God then there is ſomething God hath appo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nted as a way to God, which muſt be learned before God can be known, wherein the creature muſt be principled, which muſt turn the mind towards God, before the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture know God, ſeeing God is not known to the world, till the creature be turned out of the world: So ſaith Chriſt, <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e knows the Father, but to whom the Son reveals him:</hi> ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou have got the name of God to talk on; but when you ſhould come to principle peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the way to him, you ſay, God is it: which if bare ſaying God is it, be all thou can do, in way of teaching, then you may ſtop your mouths (if it be not for loſing your gain) for all can ſay that there is a God as<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> well as thou; yea, the Devil can preach that doctrine, but thou knows if thou had anſwered this Query to the ſatisfaction of any honeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, then thou muſt have confeſſed to the light that God hath given<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 12.</note> in Chriſt Jeſus, to lead out of darkneſs, but that deſtroys the Devils Kingdom; and therefore all his Miniſters are deaf of that ear, and ſo children of darkneſs, and keep others ſo.</p>
               <p>2. Query, Whether they are a Church of Chriſt, that beat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them that witneſs forth the truth in his name? And to this thou anſwered, That its poſſible for a true Church to be guilty of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries; but to cover thy guilt in this, thou would rank us amongſt Turks and Witches; wherein thou ſhows how thou would order theſe injuries done to us, if it were in thy power. And further, to hide thy ſelf from anſwering, thou bids us ask this queſtion of the <hi>Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition,</hi> and thoſe who have ſhed the blood of ſo many hundred thouſand true Chriſtians, &amp;c. I ſay, we are asking it of the ſame ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Prieſts: who have all along been the cauſe of ſhedding that innocent blood, where they could prevail with the powers of the earth, to act their bloody ends under religious pretences, calling that hereſie that croſſeth their luſts, as its well known, You ceaſe not to preſſe the Power to it ſtill, and prevail as far as you can, and where
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118741:10"/>
you can, and have uſed many waies ſecretly and openly, to undermine them where you cannot, and where the Magiſtrate is not ready to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute your deſigns, you have ſome of the baſer ſort ready with you, that will do it at your commands: as ſome of you Prieſts have ſet them on, ſaying, fight lads for the Goſpel. Nay, I can make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear of above 30 of you, who have fought with your own hands, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them to the ſhedding of much blood, even by the high-way, when the innocent have but paſſed by. And now wherein do you differ from them who ſhed the blood of the Martyrs, unleſs it be in this, that they would forbear till they had ſome ſhew of authority: which you cannot but fall on with your own hands, ſhewing your thirſt to be greater then ever theirs was, and your ſelves more ſhameleſs: Now if it be not an offence to judge you after Chriſts rule, then find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you to be in the ſame fruit, we muſt know the ſame Generation all along; and we bleſs our God who hath chained the Devil that he muſt but only manifeſt himſelf in caſting ſome of us into Priſon for our tryal, but cannot have h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s will further, but to ſhew what he would do if he had power; Praiſes to our God for ever.</p>
               <p>3. Quaery, Thou ſays is about Infants Baptiſin; And not being able to prove thy practice herein, either by command or example, thou ſhufles it off with telling of a Book, and asking a Quaery to the Anabaptiſts, nothing at all to the purpoſe, yet leaſt thou ſhould be found out of thy fathers work, thou infolds a lie in it, ſaying, The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abaptiſts are our Founders.</p>
               <p>And 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. Quaeries, Thou ſaiſt are all about Tythes, but takes a ready way to eſcape them; Inſtead of anſwering falls a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioning, ſhewing thy ſelf to be one of thoſe, who can ſooner ſtart queſtions then anſwer them; and inſtead of anſwering ſix of ours, thou ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts ten of thy own.</p>
               <p>Thy firſt is, Whether we have read any of thoſe Books, that proves that Tythes are ſtill of Divine Right; I ſay, by no other Divinity then the Popes authority, canſt thou nor all his Clergy prove Tythes to Chriſts Miniſters to be by Divine Right; therefore we deny the Pope, his Divinity, his Clergy, and all their lying Books, and challenge thee and all thy Generation to prove it by the Book of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>Thy 2. and 3. Quaeries, Is whether the Scripture doth warrant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man to dedicate part of his Lands to God for the ſervice of his Church, and is it not lawful to take what is ſo dedicated; and thou inſtances them that ſold their Lands in the Apoſtles times.</p>
               <p>I ſay, ſuppoſe that be granted, that a man may freely give his own to God; muſt the hireling therefore take mens goods againſt their wills, to maintain ſuch a Miniſtry and Worſhip as God never ſet up, but is denyed by him, and all that ever he ſent; nor did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles put the price of other mens Lands into their purſes, but it was diſtributed to ſuch as had need; and when your Miniſtry brings forth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118741:10"/>
the like effect: then take food and raiment freely, as the Apoſtles did, but in the mean time do not you ſpoil mens goods by force, and call them Robbers of Churches.</p>
               <p>4. Quaery, If our Anceſtors having given to the church the Tenths, are not thoſe Church-robbers that now take them away? I ſay, If my Father had given the Tenth Land in my field to the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, then had he given his own, and no right had I to have gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed that he ſhould have given what was his, but that he could give the tenth Sheaf, Pig, Gooſe or Egg, which is Gods bleſſing and the fruits of my labors, and never was his, that I deny, and he is the thief that takes the fruits of another mans labors againſt his will; for if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſow no corn, thou haſt no ſheaf, and if I have no Sow, thou haſt no P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo if my labors you take, which never was my Fathers: but who gave you money out of Servants wages, and for ſmoak paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up peoples Chimneys, Cryſomes and Mortuaries, and ſuch like, which you had all from your Anceſtor the Pope, from whom you had your firſt riſe, Tythes, and maintainance all your Pariſh Prieſts; who ſo dearly tendred his Children, that leaſt they ſhould want, provided that there ſhould be no profit, but they ſhould be ſure of their ſhare, providing you a houſe in every Pariſh to ſleep in, making you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and this Spiritual Courts to force people to work for you, that you might be ſure to have enough, whoſoever wanted; and ſince thoſe fell, you have been hard put to it, and ſore, afraid you are, leaſt the earthly powers ſhould leave you, for if they do, your Goſpel will ſtarve you; ſuch is the fruits of your plowing and ſowin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo your maintenance is as ancient as the Man of Sin, and no elder, and you muſt fall together as you have ſtood together.</p>
               <p>5. Quaery, If one that bears the bag, prove a <hi>Judas</hi> or Thief<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one <hi>Nicolas</hi> a Deacon, ſhould lead a Sect of <hi>Nicholaitans</hi> your Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: were all the Apoſtles therefore Thieves, or all the Churches and Paſtors greedy Dogs, for taking much more then the Tenth, even mens whole Eſtates, that gave them to that uſe?</p>
               <p>I ſay, That the <hi>Nicholaitans</hi> is our Predeceſſors, is one Lie, and that the Apoſtles took mens whole Eſtates, that's another, ſo we think it not ſtrange, to ſuffer with them.</p>
               <p>But you that take mens labors againſt their wills, by force, are much worſe then <hi>Judas,</hi> and more greedy then all the dumb Dogs we read on, who though they were (may be) as covetous as you, yet they were never ſo ſhameleſs as to take it by force, and plead for it, and having got a pretence of a law to cover you, it muſt not be called <hi>Thievery:</hi> but a while will that hide you, God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118741:11"/>
is about to lay you open, and the Mountains muſt not cover you; then woe to you.</p>
               <p>Thy 6. is, Whether you ask ſo much of people as Quakers do: Thou ſhameleſſe man, whom do we ask any thing on? We abhor thy beggerly practice herein, and are fed freely; prove whom we have burthened, or asked any thing on: but may be you will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe your asking, with taking it by force.</p>
               <p>7 Qu. If it be not a wrong to the people more then the Miniſters; to have the ſtanding Church-maintenance taken away, why then do people petition ſo hard for Augmentations, where means is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? or elſe do worſe: I ſay, becauſe <hi>Babylons</hi> wares are grown Coſtly, and the Merchants rich: time was, when 50 pounds would have hired a Prieſt, which now will not ſerve under 500, yet his ſtuffe no better, but much worſe; and this muſt needs be raiſed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the people have it or no, and ſo they muſt petition for Augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: but he is blind who believes this is done to right the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their wrongs, which layes ſo many 1000 pounds upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of this Nation, more then was formerly: you are rightly called leaders of the blind; if your followers ſee no further, but to believe you herein, you may keep thoſe you have blinded as long as you can, but where the eye is open, you are ſeen, and your end.</p>
               <p>The ſum of thy 8. Quaery, If the Rulers may lay Exciſe or Taxes; why not a ſettled maintenance for you? I ſay, becauſe the one is allowed on in the Scripture; but the Magiſtrate was never to force a maintenance for the Miniſtry, neither under Law nor Goſpel; but God ever took care for them that are his; and are you Chriſts Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that pleads for ſettled means? Is he grown leſſe Careful for his? nay, its you that knowes him not, therefore dare not truſt him, but envies ſuch as do.</p>
               <p>In thy 9. and 10. Thou tells of God commanding a ſufficient maintenance; And asks what Scripture forbids taking of Tythes: And ſayes God hath left it to humane prudence to judge what is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, before they give it. And thou tells the old lye over again, ſaying, The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> took more then the tenths; I ſay, out of thy own mouth be thou judged, and thy generation, who takes it where humane prudence judges not fit to give you, even from them, who reap nothing by you, and that God hath commanded any mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at all for the hirelings, I deny; on any thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by force of Law, for his own, or any other way but freely. And he that reads <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. with the firſt verſe of the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, may ſee Tythes preached down, Prieſts, and Prieſthood, that did receive them, though they never had the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by force.</p>
               <p>10. Qu. Whether Chriſt enlightens every one that cometh into the world: And thy anſwer is; All that come into the world of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he enlightens with the light of nature, and this thou ſayes is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118741:11"/>
begotten by the Book of the Creature: And all that comes into the world of grace, he enlightens with the light of ſupernatural Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: I ſay, Thou haſt plainly ſhewed thy knowledge of Chriſt, and his way of working, who ſays, That light wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch Chriſt enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Creatures with, is begotten by the Creatures Book; and this light which is ſo begotten, which thou calls natural, is all the light the Creature hath till he comes into the world of grace: Then (ſaiſt thou) he is enlightned with a ſupernatural Light. Thou blinde guide, doth any light lead into the world of grace, as thou calls it, but the light of Chriſt, and is that begotten by the Creatures Book? Art not thou Antichriſt, who art ſetting up another way out of the world, then Chriſt and his light, who ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the world, he that follows me, ſhall not abide in darkneſs:</hi> Was this light natural, or begotten by the Creatures Book? was that a natural light, that Covenant of light that God promiſed to give into the world, which the Prophets propheſied of, and <hi>John</hi> bare witneſs of, ſaying, <hi>This is the true light that enlightens every one that comes into the world: And this is the condemnation that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs:</hi> Did ever any give ſuch a teſtimony of the light, which God ſent into the world, to call it natural, and ſay, Its begotten by the book of the Creature? Art not thou a blinde guide indeed, yet being told of it, calls it railing; where thou might as well ſay Chriſt railed, who told ſuch blinde guides (who denyed the corner Stone) what they was, yet was they never ſo blinde as thou, for they did not deny but <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be the light of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he came; but thou ſays he is come, and yet art ſetting up a creature light; and to blinde the buſineſs with, thou addes a heap of Quaeries: 1. Whether this light be ſufficient to leave men without excuſe; or is it ſufficient to ſalvation? I ſay, both to condemn ſuch as love their evil deeds, and to lead to life all that follow it, <hi>John</hi> 3. 19. and 8. 12. 2. Was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient before <hi>Chriſt</hi> preached the Goſpel, or is it now ſufficient to all that never heard the Goſpel? If ſo, is not the Goſpel needleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I ſay, all that believed in him to come, had ſufficiently of his light to guide them, in what <hi>God</hi> then required; but when he was come, then the Goſpel was preached to every <hi>Creature</hi> under Heaven, then all was called to repent, and wait for the Kingdom of God, which was at hand within them, which they did not know who denyed the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht, yet the light be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng come into the world, was their condemnation; and thus the Goſpel is not a needleſs thing, but the power of <hi>God</hi> to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all that receive it: for as many as received the light, to them he gave power to become the Sons of God, to the reſt it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. 3. Quaery, If the world have ſufficient light, what need they your teaching? I ſay, to exhort them to that light, to wait and abide in it, it being the hirelings have blinded that eye, this time of the Myſtery of Iniquity hath been working, which was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118741:12"/>
began in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time; and to open this eye was <hi>Paul</hi> ſent, and<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 6.</note> to turn them from darkneſs to this light; and this anſwers thy fifth Query, why <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent to open the blind eyes and turn to light.</p>
               <p>4. Query, If all have ſufficient light within them, What need there any converting grace? That's converting grace that hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all men, teaching us to deny all ungodlineſs, and worldly<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tit.</hi> 11. 12.</note> luſts, which ſuch as thou turns into laciviouſneſs, and will not be taught by it, therefore lives in ſin, and pleads, So you muſt do while you live; and thou in ſcorn bids us rub our eyes, and tells thee, if all have it, why did we pronounce thee to be in darkneſs? I ſay, becauſe thou denies the light, and follows it not: ſo that light that's in thee is become darkneſs, and great is that darkneſs, as doth appear: who art lying again, ſaying, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are our Teachers, but art in the Reliques of their worſhip thy ſelf; for which we with the light deny them and thee, and your teaching.</p>
               <p>Our 11. Query, Whether thou haſt ſeen Gods face? And to this thou utters a deal of confuſion, ſaying, That by the eye of reaſon, thou haſt ſeen God to be infinite incomprehenſible: and ſaith, none hath ſeen God; and then asks a Query, Whether he that hath ſeen God do abhor himſelf as <hi>Job</hi> did? and ſays, is it likely that ever thoſe men had the true knowledge of God, who exalt themſelves as having the Spirit, and being perfect men without ſin?</p>
               <p>I ſay, Art not thou aſhamed of thy folly, who would perſwade peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that having the Spirit, and being without ſin could keep from ſeeing God. Thou blind ſot, Can any come to know God but by the Spirit? and where wilt thou have this Spirit if not within? Can he be any of Chriſts who hath not his Spirit? or can any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9.</note> thing ſtand before God, or come in his ſight? But if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs this Spirit, and ſanctification by it, thy filthy mind calls it pride. Bluſh for ſhame! Did ever any but the Devil, miniſter againſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Spirit, or freedom from ſiu? How art thou afraid thy fathers Kingdom ſhould fall? Yet being told of this, thou calls it railing, as thy fore-fathers would be ever in the Devils work, but would not be called his Children; but would call God their father, but hated all that was in his work, as thou doſt.</p>
               <p>12. Query, Whether you have the ſame infallible Spirit as the holy men of God had, who ſpoke forth the Scripture? And inſtead of anſwering plainly, thou falls a lying again, ſaying, thou hears the croakings of our Papiſt guides; and thou wouldſt thruſt us in with them, becauſe we ſay the Spirit is infallible; and they ſay that their Church is infallible: ſo that for us to ſay the Spirit of God is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118741:12"/>
is Popery; but what Religion is thine who cannot bear it, to ſay the Spirit is infallible? Where muſt the infallibility be, in your Church, or in the Letter, or in you Prieſts? It is likeſt thou intends the laſt: becauſe you would bind all to believe your meanings; but when thou writes again, deal plainly, and tell us where thou would have it, ſince it muſt not be in the spirit. But to the Anſwer, thou ſays, the Prophets and Apoſtles, were guided infallibly in the manner and matter; ſo that what they writ to the Church was true; but thou haſt no ſuch infallibility. I ſay, if thou had ſuch a Spirit, your Pulpits would have more truth, and thy Book not ſo full of lies as it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but wilt thou not call it railing, if I tell thee, that thou who haſt not that Spirit, haſt the Spirit of the Devil? If thou do, yet the truth is no leſs; for the Spirit of God is but one, and who hath it, hath an infallible guide, in matter and manner if he keep to it. And he that is not guided by this, hath the Spirit of Satan, and I know that ſo far as any are led by the Spirit, it guides into all truth if it be not erred from.</p>
               <p>But ſays thou, I ſhall never like ſuch pretenders to the Spirit. I know thou doſt not; for that guide leads out of thy Kingdom. Sayeſt thou, All true Chriſtians are certain of their Fundamentals, yet with doubting.</p>
               <p>Here thou haſt declared thy damned foundation; but true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians know a foundation without doubting; and thou falls to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring us with the Pope, and would make us like him.</p>
               <p>I ſay, were it not we cry down his Worſhip, means; and authority, that remains in you, we ſhould not have ſo much of your malice. Are not you his dear Children, as like as may be? Have you ſo ſoon forgot who be got you into your Parſonages, and Maſterſhips, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained you, and your place, and form of Worſhip? He is but a young Prieſt, who was not Conſecrated by his Cathedral Order, though now you ſee the Biſhops your Maſters are down with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and the people. You can talk againſt them, as they did againſt the Pope their Maſter, when the Kings would own him no longer, nor they could not be ſuffered to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs his authority in this Nation, then they would rather turn than fly; and have not you ſtuck to Epiſcopal Worſhip, till you ſee you were like to be turned out, and then your wiſdom would convince you of your error.</p>
               <p>Is not he blind that ſees not you one with the <hi>Papiſt</hi> in the main? Its not getting into their houſes, and talking againſt them that can blind us, when we ſee their foundation-ſtanding; and not one thing you do, which is as the Apoſtles or believers did it: But either<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as the Pope and his Councels invented, or as you have invented ſince in your Councels: but never came to the Saints form, much leſs to the power, For ſhame be ſilent in this buſineſſe; till you have more hopes of hiding your ſelves,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118741:13"/>
you have loſt your old way of ſtopping preaching and printing, and now your ſlandering your Popery upon other mens backs, will but cauſe all to ſee you more plainly: people are now grown ſo wiſe as they begin to know the tree by its fruit; your words will not ſerve, your Covering growes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, it muſt be rent, and your refuge of lies are a ſweeping away, your rowing in your own filth doth but caſt dung in your own faces: the truth is living and pure, and will clear it ſelf, and all that abide in it, but ſhame ſhall cover the wicked.</p>
               <p>And thou calls the Ranters our brethren, but they are your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and hearers, they come not amongſt us, unleſſe it be to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as you do; there is no more Communion with us and you, then light and darkneſſe; will this cover you who have them with you, preaching to them, and they maintaining you? nay, its well known that there is none ſo bad in the Nation, but if he have but any thing to adde to your hire, you are for him, and he is one of your Church, and brotherhood; is there either Drunkard, Swearer, or Whoremonger whatſoever, but you will reap his Carnals, with, or againſt his will, and you will tell him you ſow to him ſpirituals, and ſuch is your ſeed, and ſuch fruits comes on it, yet thy ſhameleſſe lips will call ſuch our brethren, when we have turned from them for theſe filthineſſes, and you have received them with it, nay, ſome of you boaſt of ſuch Converts, when we have denyed them.</p>
               <p>13. Qu. What is hells mouth that the wicked go in at? And to this thou ſayes it ſufficeth thee to know that hell is a ſtate of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſery, where ſuch as we ſhall everlaſtingly bear Gods wrath. I ſay, that's thy deſire to know? but wert thou not blind, thou wouldſt know, it is for liars, ſlanderers, the man of ſin, and his diſciples, who plead for his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>14 Qu. Whether the Bible be the Word of God? and <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the Goſpel? and whether there were any Goſpel before them? and whether they be the light? and to this thou gives not anſwer, but tells of a temporal Word; ſo much knowes thou of that word that endures for ever, and a word that is a ſign of Gods mind, and ſuch confuſed ſtuffe, and tells of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſenſe betwixt Chriſt, the Scriptures; and thou ſayes it was written that it might be a ſtanding rule, and kept intire, and ſure; to the worlds end; but how often have you and your generation altered this rule? inſomuch as ſcarce two of you can agree about it: what is the meaning of it, and how many Copies is there of it? which of them is the ſtanding rule? that which ſtands moſt ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to your wills and pleaſures, and how intire is it kept,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118741:13"/>
when much of it is quite loſt; but thou might have ſaid of it, as of the infallible Spirit, if the letter be not it, thou haſt none thou knows on, that had been plainer dealing; and thou ſayes this word is the Light, but not as Chriſt is the Light, or the Spirit, for there are many lights, and ſo with thy many lights thou ſhews thy ſelf to be ignorant of the one light the Scriptures ſpeaks of, which holds out but one light and word, but thou haſt many in the dark-lanthorn of thine imaginations not one like another, and ſo imagines that Chriſt, the Spirit, and the Word are not one, nor enlightens all alike; ſayeſt thou, mans reaſon is the eye, and the Goſpel is externall, and the Spirit clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth theſe two together, and ſo breedeth a ſpirituall illumination, which the word a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone could not procure, whereas the Scriptures witneſs the word, by which alone all externalls were made, and the word for reconciling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and making new: but ſayeſt thou, the word without reaſon and externalls cannot produce; and this is thy word thou preaches, and ſo it ſeems by what it produces.</p>
               <p>And thou asks ſome queries, 1. Whether we believe the Scriptures be true; I ſay yea, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayes thou, they call themſelves the word of God, and thou brings ſome ſcriptures to prove it, but not one that ſayes the letter is the word, and thou brings <hi>Rom. 10. 8. The word is nigh you, even in your heart, and in your mouth;</hi> but is the Bible there: and thou brings 1 <hi>Pet. 1. 25. The word of God endures for ever,</hi> and before called it the temporall word: Thy 2. qu. Will we give you leave to ſmel the Pope, in our endeavours to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſgrace the Scriptures though our noſe be ſtopt: I ſay, were thou not ſtark blind and drunck with envie, thou might ſee thy own confuſed ſcornfull ſpirit, with which thou haſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered thy folly, who one while will have the word temporall, and another while to endure for ever; and to prove the Bible to be the Word, brings, <hi>the word is in the heart,</hi> but no wonder thou be blind, who ſayes mans reaſon is the eye.</p>
               <p>15. <hi>query.</hi> Whether you own revelations or no: And to this thou ſayes, thou owns all divine revelations, and diſowns all diabollicall ones, but in thy 10. page, hath denyed revelations, but the revelations thou own is what is written, but hath not the Devil theſe alſo, yes, and can preach them as wel as you, and take them to plead for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as wel as thou, yet ſayes thou, theſe are able to make men wiſe to ſalvation, without any further additions, and when thou haſt done, ſayes, they muſt have the Spirit of Chriſt to help them; but thou might do wel to ſhew thy opinion, whether the Spirit can make wiſe to alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without them, it ſeems to be thy opinion that it is not, by thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer query, where thou asks, whether the light of Chriſt be ſufficient; where your Goſpel is not preached, which no Goſpel you have but the Letter, which if you had it not, you would be as dumb as thoſe which <hi>Iſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ab</hi> ſpeaks on, and in thy concluſion thou tels of other helps which are o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſlat neceſſity beſides the Spirit, and thy litterall revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which before thou ſaid was ſufficient to ſalvation without any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118741:14"/>
but by thy own words, if there had been no Book thou had had no revelation, and yet in words ſeems to deny thy father the Pope, who hath kept thee thy revelations, elſe thou had been without for ought thou knows, yet you cannot beare it to be called miniſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit, and the Apoſtles was Miniſters not of the Letter but of the Spirit; this with you is railing.</p>
               <p>19. <hi>qu.</hi> Is about ſinging <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms, and for anſwer to this thou ſends us to a Book of <hi>Cottons</hi> and <hi>Ford,</hi> and ſay thou knows no reaſon why thou ſhould add any more; a pretty ſhuffle to get ſhut of that thou canſt not prove; yet though thou have loſt thy reaſon to anſwer, thou wil ask more queres, 1. If the Scripture be written for our uſe, why may not we ſpeak to God in <hi>Davids</hi> words? I ſay becauſe <hi>David</hi> would not keep a lyar in his houſe, may thou who art found a lyar, ſing theſe words; the Scripture was not written by ſuch a Spirit, nor to ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, nor doth ſuch learn ought by the Letter, but to cover thy ſhame, and deceive others, as appears by thy practiſe.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>que.</hi> They being uſed by the Church till the Apoſtles time, where was they aboliſhed? I ſay is that Church thou means on the Phariſees, ſuch a Church uſes them now, though not ſo wel as they did, for they did not put them into rimes as you do, and when the Saints ſung with the Spirit and with underſtanding, and he that had a Pſalm ſung his own and not anothers, then was the way of Phariſees aboliſhed: 3. <hi>qu.</hi> Whether is it more lawful for us to ſing in the words of <hi>David,</hi> or for you to take together all the ſharp reproofes in Scripture to rail on me with; I ſay there is as much betwixt the lawfulneſs of them, as betwixt truth and a lye, for when we take Scripture language by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that gave it forth to reprove the ſame deceit in thee, which Chriſt and his Prophets and Apoſtles did in the chiefe Prieſts, Phariſees and Hirelings, then we ſpeak truth, though thou call it railing, but when thou and thy hearers ſings <hi>Davids</hi> words, ſaying, you have no ſcornfull eye; you have rored all the day long, your bones hath quaked, you have made your bed to ſwim with tears, no lyar ſhall dwel in your houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not a neſt of lyars all found lying toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and he that ſayes otherwiſe of you, is a lyar like you.</p>
               <p>17. <hi>qu.</hi> What is the ſoul of man, &amp;c. And thou ſayes it's the cauſe of our life, I ſay thou knows not him who is the cauſe of our life, no more then thou doſt the ſoul, but here thou would deny God to be the cauſe of life, and put the ſoul in his ſtead, as thou haſt denyed the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to ſet the letter in his ſtead, ſo art thou drawing downward as faſt as thou canſt; but ſayes thou, the whole man in Scripture is taken for<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an the cauſe of life dye or be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed?</note> the ſoul, ſo by thy opinion, the man is the cauſe of life, ſo thou haſt ſhewed what life thou lives, and what thou knows of the ſoul, yet thou wilt ask more queries though reſolve none; and firſt thou begins to wrangle with the command of Chriſt that forbids thy maſter-hood, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing; is not many words in the Scriptures tranſlated maſter, of as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> low and humble importance as ruler, I ſay the words of Chriſt was ever in the way of the Hirelings, and Phariſees, and Prieſts, and their pride,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118741:14"/>
but they could not get them removed, though they was vext at them, and would not have them applyed to them no more than thou, but let his words alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou muſt not wreſt them out of their place and power, thou canſt not bow them but muſt bow to them, they was given to break thee and thy pride, and not to be broken by thee nor thy teachings.</p>
               <p>2, <hi>qu.</hi> Thou ſayes if God bid people obey you as Rulers, and the quakers perſwade people to reject you as Serpents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is to be obeyed, God or the quakers? and whether is the Spirit of God or of the Devil the quakers ſpeaks by? I ſay, God did never bid people o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Hirelings, and ſuch as are out of the Doctrine of Chriſt (as you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) but the Spirit of God called ſuch Serpents, and ſo doth now, which is not the Spirit of the Devil, as the Devil would ſlander it to be both<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 33.</note> then and now, you being now found in the ſame practiſe, are reproved with the ſame ſpirit.</p>
               <p>3. <hi>qu.</hi> Thou asks, Is it the Miniſters or quakers that have the rule over people, and wait for the good of ſouls? I ſay the quakers abhors ſuch rule as you bear; and for the good of ſouls, thou muſt firſt know what the ſoul is before thou can watch for the good of it, nay thou watches to deſtroy ſouls for diſhoneſt gain, hirelings was never ſouls ſhepheards.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>qu.</hi> Thou ſayes if the preſent Paſtors be not true Miniſters, tell you who are, and where you may find them, and where they have been from Chriſt til now? I ſay thoſe are true miniſters and ever was, who wandred to and fro, having no certain dwelling place, of whom the world was not worthy, who ever bore witneſs againſt the falſe Prophets that bear rule by their means, and the Prieſts that preached for hire, and the people that loved to have it ſo, and whoſe manner was to go into the Synagogues, and Idols temples to diſprove the hirelings falſe worſhip, and call people from them to the true ſhepheard; and you may find many of theſe in the moſt priſons of the nation for ſo doing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by your means, againſt whom we are ſent to witneſs, and theſe have been baniſhed to and fro, (ſince the myſtery of iniquity, and the popiſh prieſthood was ſet) up into corners, but now are come to light, to witneſs againſt the myſtery of iniquity, therefore do the heathen rage, the man of ſin and all his miniſters, becauſe his end is near.</p>
               <p>5. <hi>qu.</hi> Thou asks if it will be for the peoples profit, to deſpiſe their Teachers and guides? I ſay you who have deſpiſed Chriſts commands to ſet up your own luſts, and pride, covetouſneſs, and falſe-worſhip, muſt be deſpiſed, and when ſuch guides are diſcovered, then ſhal the people profit when they come to be guided with that ſpirit God hath given to every man to profit withall, which thou wil keep them from as long as you can; that you may fil up your meaſure, and wrath come upon you to the uttermoſt, being captivated by the Devil ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the God of this world having blinded the eye, ſo that the Goſpell<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> is hid from you, and you loſt, letting up the Letter inſtead of it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118741:15"/>
denyed the light, and erred from it, are got up into hardneſs of heart, impriſoning, beating, and making havock like mad beaſts, what ever the Devill did where he reigned, ſo do you, being the head of the Serpent, which Chriſt is come to bruiſe, as he did in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo he is the ſame for ever to the ſame brood, who now are found in the ſame bloody plots againſt the ſeed of God, worſe than ever any, ſeeking the lives of others, for practiſing that in life which your ſelves wil preach in words for money, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch a generation of raging beaſts was never yet in the world, who ſeek to devour on every ſide you, and who departs from ſin is your prey, the greateſt deceivers thatever yet come; now when you come to be revealed, who would have bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eved that you, who have had ſo many millions of pounds for teaching people to forſake ſin, and now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if any declare that he hath forſaken it and is ſet free, you preach it down as the moſt dangerous error that ever was, and cry out to drunckards, ſwearers, thieves and murderers, and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, come not near them leaſt you be deceived, and now get up more money for preaching up ſin while the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtands, than you took for preaching it down, yet if we tel you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you are bringing people into Covenant with the Devil for tear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of life, you ſay we rail on you when you have be got the faith of that Covenant in the whole nation, ask any that ever believes your teaching, if they believe that Chriſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> able to redeem them from committing ſin in this world, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are ready to give an account of their faith, nay none can be free he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, but when they are dead in another world they ſhall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the faith and covenant is ſutable for no leſs time then till men can ſin no longer, and if any have broke this Covenant through the righteous Covenant, they are ready to ſtone him, yet leaſt thou ſhould be ſeen in this filth, you caſt a miſt before the ſimple, ſaying you muſt ſtrive after perfection and freedom, and purity, and to be ſet free from ſin, but once, knowing that unbeliefe is in the bottome, there is little dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of freedome, for the Devil whoſe work you are doing, knows ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel that if he can but have people to believe they cannot be free, he knows they are ſafe with him for ever comming at it, no faith, no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, according to every mans faith ſo ſhall it be unto them, and that ſtriving which is not in faith to obtain, is ſelfe-righteouſneſs, but<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25.</note> who believes that Chriſt is able to ſave to the uttermoſt? all that come to God by him ſhall ſee it ſo, but this the blind knows not, who would have believed that theſe Prieſs that now is, had been the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors that ever was before them, who have preached ſo long againſt it? but ſay you, this perſecution of ours is not as theirs was, they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Chriſt and ſuch as he ſent, but theſe are wandrers and Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, and diſturbs our peace and worſhips, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but the light is come, your myſts wil not hide you, the Sun is riſen, and you are ſeen in the work againſt the ſame Spirit, nothing altered but the perſons, or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or time, where had ever miniſters of Chriſt hand in perſecuting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon any account whatſoever, prove your practiſe herein: Then
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118741:15"/>
thou goes on to tell what that death is that paſſed upon all men, and thou ſayes its the ſeparation of the ſoul from the body; thou blind for, did not death paſs upon <hi>Adam</hi> til ſoul and body was ſeparated? this is like thy opinion of the ſoul; but how canſt thou who art in death know what it is? thoſe whom Chriſt quickned, who were dead, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 2. 1. 5. was they ſuch who had no ſouls? nay, thou muſt own the Light before thou know what death is, death reigns in lyars and envious ones.</p>
               <p>18. <hi>qu.</hi> What is the Flaming Sword that keeps the Tree of Life &amp; the Cherubims? and this thou anſwers with calling it a fooliſh queſtion, and adds a lye to it, ſaying, we have not ſeen it, thou ſayes it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice thee to know there is ſuch a thing (which knowledg is no more in thee but hearſay) but the ſight thou puts far off into the world to come, and the Tree of Life alſo, for thou that never ſaw the Flaming Sword &amp; Cherubims, never came near the Tree of Life, but as I ſaid before, feeds upon death, thy own curſed carnall knowledg, which God hath forbidden.</p>
               <p>19. <hi>qu.</hi> Whether they that ſtand praying in the Synagogues or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols Temples, and love greetings in Markets, and bind heavie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens on the people, &amp; are called of men maſters, be not out of Chriſts Doctrine? and this falling upon the head of the Serpent, being thy own practiſe, thou art forced to take thy old crooked winding wayes to get out, and thou begins to queſtion inſtead of anſwer, ſaying if your Temples be Chriſt Temples, do not we make Chriſt an Idoll by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them Idolls Temples? I ſay, they are not Chriſt Temples, unleſs thou mean the Pope be he, whoſe Temples they are, who builded and conſecrated them into the names of dead men and women, and ſet up in them a dead worſhip, all which Chriſt never commanded, but the Temple of Chriſt is made without hands, and there he dwells, and not in Temples made with hands, haſt thou a face to father thoſe upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, wherein you generation of blood-ſuckers have worſhipped in them ever ſince they was builded? do not they ſtand witneſſes againſt you, that you are the children of them who ſlew the Martyrs, and now are found beating in the ſame SYNAGOGUES, and ſhedding Blood as far as you can get the ſame power by which they did it, <hi>CHRIST</hi> had never ſuch TEMPLES, ſtop thy MOUTH for SHAME. And thou goes on, and where thou cannot deny but thou art in the ſteps of the PHARISEES<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet ſayes thou, I do not love it, they loved it to be called Maſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I do not; wel, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſayes in words thou loves it not, but come to thy practiſe, and it wil appear thou who art but one, haſt made more ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and crooked wayes to uphold it in this thy book, then all the generations of thy fathers the Phariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that ever was before thee, and doſt thou think to cover all this by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou loves it not, but you have uſed ſo long to lead the bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd, that you would put out the eys of them that ſee, &amp; thou ſaies it was phariſes pride that was condemned, I ſay ſo it is your pride that is your condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118741:16"/>
nor can thou clear thy ſelf of the very ſame things they was found in; but leaſt thou ſhould loſe all, yet ſayes thou, Chriſt bids them hear the hypocriticall phariſees, and obſerve to do as they bid you; I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, to plead for hypocriticall teachers is the likeſt way to get in, to have people commanded to hear you, had not you run ſo groſs til you have loſt all alſo, even the outward form of godlineſs which they had, and upon that account he bad hear them, becauſe they ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat, and read the Letter truly without adding, but you are neither ſet in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeat nor Chriſts, but run in your own imaginations, till nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Law, nor Goſpel-letter wil warrant any one thing of your worſhip, matter, nor manner, means nor maintenance, as I ſhall be ready to prove, that not one particular of your worſhip, you act in your Idolls Temples, nor wages for ſo doing, can you prove by plain Scripture to be ſo much as in the form, commanded o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> practiſed by Chriſt and his Saints, and yet calls your ſelves upr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ght and faithful miniſters; for ſhame be ſilent as to boaſting, til you acquit your ſelves of this charge by plain Scriptures without wreſting it; and would you have us bound to hear ſuch under pretence of hypocrites, who have loſt both power and ſhew of Godlineſs? and ſayes thou, it is not being called maſter that Chriſt intended; thou lying ſpirit, would thou make him a lyar like thee, did not he intend as he ſpoke? or thou takes him to be an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite like the Phariſees, whom thou would thruſt in amongſt with thy conſequence; and thou ſayes he forbids the name of fathers; I ſay, he forbids not children and fathers, but ſuch as you, then thou goes on in thy old way, lying, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng we forbid the owning of any relations, and all affections and reſpects to them; I ſay thy father hath fitted thee with boldneſs to bring forth his work, who dare declare thy own ſhame to all that know our practiſe, what diſ-affection canſt thou charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon any of our relat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons, unleſs thou accuſe us becauſe we cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Devils pride and bow to it in ſuch as thee?</p>
               <p>And to plead for this maſterſhip further thou ſayes, thou wil tel us ſomething we know not, and that is, that the diſciples of the ſect-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Phariſees, ſo gloryed in their maſters, that they were ready to go by the ears, and kil one another, and this thou would ſend us to ſee amongſt them as a ſtrange buſineſs, which we ſee daily amongſt you and your diſciples, how many Sects and Sect-maſters is amongſt you Prieſts and your Diſciples, and have been all by the ears as thou calls it, even unto blood, til you have vented all your envie againſt the Lambs of Chriſt, as they did then, though thou would put it far off, yet we ſee it here preſent, and ſayeſt thou, theſe called they Rabbies, as the Papiſts do the Pope, but why wilt thou not read on one wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d further, as your hearers do you, no doubt but this is as true though not ſo much for thy purpoſe, who art hiding thy ſelfe, by accuſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and ſo now, that I have ſet thee in, thou may read on all the reſt of thy charge againſt the Pope, and find thy ſelfe guilty, and ſtop thy mouth, and ſee the Phariſees, the Pope, and thee, and thy brethren,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118741:16"/>
all on a Line, and that it is not words we contend about, but your whole practiſe, which being found in and condemned, words and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings cannot hide you, and if the Scriptures be not right tranſlated as thou pleads, then is leſs confidence to be put in any of you who had it in doing, yet thou ſayes its a ſtanding rule; thus Babylons Children are claſhing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one againſt another, but all againſt the Stone, by which we ſee your fruits to be the ſame with the Phariſes, change the letter as often as you will, wo to him that hath no other guide and rule but that which you have ſo often chopt and changed, and not ſtill wil it pleaſe you, thou may wel call it a temporall word, for you wil make it ſerve all times, or you muſt want of your wils; its no ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d thing with you to take <hi>Pauls</hi> words, who wandred up and down in hunger and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27.</note> coveted no mans money nor gold, nor apparell, and was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable to none, nor took ought againſt the will of the owner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with two or three conſequences and meanings from your originall, you wil make it prove you four or five hundred a yeer, and a great houſe to live in, and this you will not have by favour but force, and yet they are thieves that denies to give you their goods when you ask it, but now when your practiſe and <hi>Pauls</hi> are compared, they are as far diſtant as before, could you bend his life as you do his words to your own, then might ye deceive the elect, but God hath left this a rule for ever, by their fruits ſhall you know them; ſo by your works you are ſo farre from <hi>Paul,</hi> that you are out-run <hi>Balaam</hi> and all the falſe Prophets and greedy dogs you read on in the Scriptures, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver took it by force under pretence of a Law, taking three for one, as you do, yet this truth which is as clear as the Sun, muſt be called rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, becauſe it falls upon your deceit, and becauſe a ſervant calls ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Scripture, ſayes thou, why may not thou be ſo called, as a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter? thou may as wel ſay, becauſe a ſervant doth own his maſter, why may not I break the commands of Chriſt? and ſayes thou, <hi>Paul</hi> he was called a wiſe maſter builder, I ſay thoſe words wil not fit thee who would build up thy pride with them; he was <hi>Paul a Servant,</hi> and not <hi>Maſter Paul,</hi> if thou canſt own it thou may, if not, let it alone, I ſay thou muſt be proved by thy deeds, not with wreſting his words, nor was the maſters of aſſemblies <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpoke on, ſuch as thou, but of one ſhepheard, which the hirelings never knew, nor any who would take <hi>Solomons</hi> words to deſtroy Chriſts commands; did thou know him thou would not teach men to break one of the leaſt of them, much more that which hath ever diſtinguiſhed falſe Prophets from true, nor is there any one command more plainly expreſſed, nor more faithfully obeyed by his miniſters, then this that thou art teaching men to break, it being now the great controverſie with Chriſt and Antichriſt, who ſhould be maſter, and who ſhould be bowed to, and how loath are his miniſters to loſe it, as is ſeen by thy crooked wayes thou takes to keep it, but thou muſt loſe it, and the Lamb muſt have it, who wil not bow to thee, and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Festus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> cannot bear the out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118741:17"/>
in breaking Chriſts command, thoſe was not forbidden as thy practiſe<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 44.</note> is, who art pleading for titles of honour to you Prieſts as a duty; O ſhame thou infidel! how canſt thou believe thats ſeek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng for honour from men? was ever any m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niſter of Chriſt found in that work? and is not this the greateſt thing thou ſtands for in thy book? is it not ſeen whole honour thou art ſeeking againſt the commands of Chriſt? nor is he void of the fear of God, who denies thee to be a faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt, who miniſters againſt the command of Chriſt; nor are we ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh but we can judge who is in the work of Chriſt, and who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, with lyes, ſaying a Miniſter of Chriſt is called Maſter, and that to deny your Greek and Hebrew is to deny Chriſt, as though a naturall language was Chriſt, and thou calls ſome ſacred languages, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dolater, is not every language natural to them who are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed in them, is not our Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh as ſacred among the Greeks as theirs is here? but ſuch as thou wil worſhip any th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng rather then the Spirit; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thy lyes in this book, ſayes we are not able to charge thee with any c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime, but humaine frailt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, when thou art found full of groſs wickedneſs, as in thy book is laid open, and here thou may receive an anſwer to thy query, and thou boaſts that thou can talk better then we, I ſay thou makes it not appear in thy book, for it truth had ordered thy tongue, I had not found ſo many open falſehoods and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſions as I have laid open already, and thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayes thou would threſh, and dig, and labour, if God would give thee leave; I ſay, what a God do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t thou ſerve which will not allow of labour, our God condemns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dleneſs, and ſayes if any wil not work, neither ſhould he eat; but the God of this<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 10</note> World is the God of idleneſs and fulneſs of bread, which the Prieſts of this nation have been known to ſerve more than any one ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple elſe; and thou ſayes our prater is a lyer, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaying if thou had no pay thou would not preach; I ſay, prove him a lyar, and ſhame him, come out and preach freely, and then if he ſay ſo of thee, I ſhall ſay he is a lyar too, but I ſuppoſe thy Godwil not ſuffer thee to do this, no more than he wil ſuffer thee to labour, for theſe muſt go together; but let me ask the one queſtion amongſt all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne: <hi>qu.</hi> The Miniſters or Chriſt ſaid follow us, and walk as you have us for examples; but if<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou ſhould ſay ſo to thine, and all the Pariſh maſters in this nation alſo, and your hearers ſhould follow you as you do, what a nation would here be, all idle, all proud and covetous, all live on the ſweat of other mens brews, all Maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would not this deſtroy relations? who would you have to worſhip you? therefore take heed how you bid them ſollow you, I have heard o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome of you (may be foreſeeing part of this) have been ſo wiſe as to ſay, do as I ſay, but not as I do, I ſay this is plain dealing, compared with thee who acts all this, charges God with it, and when thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t done, ſayes we are not able to cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge thee with any crime, ſo thou would have us to charge it upon him who wil not let the labour.</p>
               <p>20. <hi>qu.</hi> Did ever the Lord of Heaven and Earth, or Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118741:17"/>
bid thee or any of you go and preach to a people? or was any of the Apoſtles or Miniſters o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt made Miniſters by the wil of man: To this thou anſwers after the old way, and begins another ſtory, telling the Lord called the Apoſtles by his own voyce, and le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t them to call one another to the end of the world, end to prove this untruth thou brings, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 21. which Chapter hath not 21. verſes in, but there is not one verſe in that chapter, nor in all the book, that ſayes that the Apoſtles was to leave ſuch an order to the end of the world, ſo that a verſe beyond number is fitteſt to quote for ſuch a ly, but what Apoſtle was that who leaſt order with the Pope, from whom all the Pariſh Teachers both in this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nation and many more, have had their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and holy order, ſince the Pops tieme he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ves from <hi>Peter,</hi> and if thou ſay ſo tool I ſhall not believe you, till I ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tter proofe than yet thou haſt quoted, but thou proceeds to deny any t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expect a call from Heaven, and the ſignes of thy call thou ſets down: Firſt, thy competent qualification, yet haſt thou nought freely, but ſo hard to ſtudy for it, that thou haſt no time to work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that never was Chriſts call nor qualification: 2. Thy thirſt after the good of ſouls, yet thou knows not what the ſoul is. 3. The ordination of authoriſed Church officers, what ſort thoſe are, and the riſe of them, hath been declared before. 4. The call of the people and their conſent over whom he hath ſet thee; I ſay none that ever was ſent by Chriſt, ever went to ask conſent of the People. 5. The ſucceſs of thy labours; but how many of thy hearers are ſet free from ſin, yea thy ſelf yet a lyar. 7. Some teſtimony of the Spirit, yet thou denies any infallibility, and that Spirit with the Spirit of God that never erred is denyed: Theſe ſeven ſayeſt thou ſet together, are the ſignes of Chriſts call, and thy miſſion, ſhew you the like if you can; to which I ſay, never any of Chriſts Miniſters ſhewed the like, nor do I neither: and thou tels the old taile over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that no immediate call ſince the Apoſtles, which thou never proved yet, and thou concludes; wil not all this ſuffice? I ſay thoſe who know not the Scriptures nor the power of God may truſt thee and be ſufficed with a lye, but who knows either, ſees whence thou art; was not <hi>Annanias,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and others in the Scriptures, called im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9, 10, 11.</note> and with the power and Spirit by which I am called im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 2.</note> do I teſtifie againſt thee with the Scripture.</p>
               <p>21. <hi>qu.</hi> Whether had any Miniſters of Chriſt an hour glaſs to preach by, or tooke a Text, and raiſed Doctrine, uſes, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Motives, or a carnall BELL to call people together by, prove theſe things by plaine SCRIPTURE, or elſe be ſilent, and never profeſs your ſelves to be Miniſters of Chriſt more; And to this thou anſwers with telling of Spectacles, Doublet, and Breeches, and ſuch like vain words, but dare not compare your practiſe with the SAINTS in <hi>SCRIPTVRE<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> thou will not be tryed by thy own ſtanding Rule, but ſayes theſe are purpoſely left by Chriſt, to be determined of humane
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118741:18"/>
providence, what providence is that which is humane providence, to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 13.</note> which your worſhip of God is leaſt, is his worſhip humane, and your tythes divine? they who worſhip in truth have the Spirit of Truth, to guide them into all truth in his whole worſhip, but your humane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, hath led you out of that worſhip in all things, and thou ſayes thou can limit thy ſelfe, and not limit the Spirit, ſo the ſpirit and thou are not one, I ſay I know ſelfe orders thee, and thy times are in thy own hands, but with Chriſt and his it never was; the query is of the manner of thy worſhip, and thou anſwers did the Apoſtles preach in Doublets and Breeches? is Doublets and Breeches forms of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? a man may alter Doublets and Breeches, but may he alter the form of worſhip which Chriſt appointed? The Saints meet together ſayes thou, and did not ſtay two or three dayes, therefore why may not I have an Hour-glaſs? I ſay they meet together, ſometimes ſtayed whole dayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſometimes whole nights, as they was moved, and this did not limit the Spirit, but can you therefore ſet an hour to begin and end for hundreds of years, by a glaſs, or by a clock either, and not limit the Spirit? if thou knew the ſpirit and its moving, thou would know to the contrary, Chriſt would not go to worſhip at his own time, nor any that knows the Spirit, but they are ordered by it, both for time and manner, but this the wolves never knew; thou ſayes if thou had our ſpirit, thou ſhould be angry at the hour-glaſs and preach the people out of their places: I ſay thou art a man pleaſer, who keeps an Hour-glaſs to pleaſe the People, and a man pleaſer can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot pleaſe God, but the hireling muſt do his work, as may aſſure him of his wages, if people ſet you your work, its fit that they ſhould have it done in their own time, and after that manner they like beſt, this we ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you, did you not pretend miniſters of Chriſt, but if Chriſt ſet a work, its as much reaſon that he ſhould have the like freedome to order his workmen, ſeeing he never ſends his to the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld for counſel nor hire, this we know, though thou doſt not: and thou ſayes Chriſt took a Text and applyed it, and this thou would bring to prove your litterall Miniſtry to be the Miniſtry of Chriſt, I ſay Chriſt took a Text and ſaid it was fulfilled in him, but if you take no Text but what is fulfilled in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 3. 5.</note> you, then you muſt take only ſuch as <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. 12, 13. and thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.</note> that tel of a Prieſthood that were called of men Maſters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bore<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 5. 31.</note> rule by their means, cryed peace while people put into their mouthes, but if not prepared wars; that were proud and covetous, taught for flecces, beat and caſt out of Synagogues, wolves in Sheeps cloathing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe and ſuch like which ſure your practiſe you muſt take, and then ſay this day is theſe Scriptures fulfilled in your ears, and then read your portion, ſo take your own, then you are no thieves; for the word of God you have not, nor was it ever preached in your manner, nor for your ends, and your dividing is to cry peace, though God hath not ſpoken peace in the conſcience, and are daubers, and tread the Lambs under your feet, read <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25. 26. and you may
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118741:18"/>
ſee what d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>viders you are, and what it is you divide.</p>
               <p>22. <hi>qu</hi> Whether are not they that bear rule by their means and ſeek for their gain from their quarter, and ſeek for the fleece, and make a prey on the people, and are hirelings, be not falſe Prophets yea or nay? and are not ſuch to be cryed out againſt now as they was then? and this being thy own condition, thou art ſo wiſe as to let it alone without an anſwer, if thou had done ſo with all the reſt thou had kep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy ſelf longer covered; thou bids us read <hi>Malachi,</hi> ſo we have, and in the ſecond Chapter, firſt and laſt, and the reſt of the Chapter, we find thy generation and thy practiſe, and your end comming on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pace.</p>
               <p>22. <hi>qu.</hi> Whether do you own trembling and quaking which the Scriptures witneſs? and this thou looks upon to be a curſe, or a papiſt trick, or mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of the deceiver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhowing thy ſelfe to be one of thoſe ſpoken of <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 66. 5. there thou may ſee thy work and ours; thou Blaſphemer, doſt thou call that a Papiſt trick and the power of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that all the Holie men of God that ever did declare the way how they came to ſee God, came through, as the Scriptures can witneſs, in <hi>Moſes, David, Daniel,</hi> the Prophets and Apoſtles, but ſayes thou, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect love caſts out fear; what now! art thou talking of perfection, is it not blaſphemy to name ſuch a word? art thou now come to perfection? thou art wel grown ſince thou begun thy book, wherein thou was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt any poſſibility of perfection, but in heaven, art thou got ſo high now? take heed thou deny it no more, leaſt thou ſhame thy ſelfe; but its not a lye that wil make thee bluſh, thou haſt caſt out that fear, but its ſelfe love that hath caſt it out, for the love of God caſts<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 11.</note> not out the fear of God, bleſſed he is that feareth alwaies, but thou art<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 5.</note> curſed who haſt caſt it out.</p>
               <p>Laſt <hi>Quaery.</hi> Whether do you ſay you ſhall be free from the body<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 14</note> of ſin while you are on the earth, and whether ſhal any be perfect yea or nay? and to this thou ſayes; thou believes that in the inſtant of death when you part with the fleſh, you part with all the remnants of ſin; I ſay thou haſt made thy confeſſion according to thy faith and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant I told thee on before, that is, you muſt part with your ſin when you are dead and can ſin no more if you would, and the devil too; but that this Covenant of hel and death ſhould be for any leſs than tearm of life, thats again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t your faith which you have preached, and live in, and againſt your Covenant too, yet if we do but ſay that you are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the devil and ſuch as uphold his Kingdome of ſin, while peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple live, and the world tands you cannot beare it, though we do but declare thy own con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſion. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or ſinleſs perfection, thou ſayes thou believes the devil bred it, and thou ſayes Chriſt deteſts it, and never man that had true grace bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eved it; I ſay, or thy ſaith that believes the devil bred perfection, I know thou art of that faith that ever called Chriſt <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zebub,</hi> and his works the Devil works, ſo in that fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th I do not expect any other confeſſion, but thy lye thou layes upon Chriſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118741:19"/>
and the Saints ſaying Chriſts deteſts it, and the Saints believed it not, I ſhall reprove and diſprove by plain Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 48. be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, even as your fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r which is in Heaven is perfect: Did he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand here what he deteſted? or was this a ſinfull perfection he called for? wouldſt thou make him a lyar and a diſſembler like thee; and for the Saints owning perfection, read <hi>Eqh. 4, 12, 13. Cal. 1. 28. Phil. 3. 15. 1 Theſſ. 3. 10. &amp; 5. 2. Pſal. 18. 32. Pſal. 101. 2. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 10. 14. 1 Cor. 2. 6. Iam. 1. 4. 2 Cor.</hi> 7. 1. with many more places, too many to ſet down here, which all declare their beliefe in perfection, and thee a falſe witneſs; preaching ſuch a faith as never any of Gods miniſters ever did, nay thou exceeds all the hirelings and falſe Prophets that ever was, never any of them durſt ſay it was of the Devill before thee, and thou ſays its the Papiſts dongue we feed upon: O thou blaſphemer! dare thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peak thus of the perfection of God, which he gives to all that wait upon him, and hunger after his righteouſneſs, thou makes it appear thou never knew the good and perfect gift that comes from<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iude</hi> 11.</note> above, thou runs too greedily after gifts and rewards from below, thou haſt blinded that eye that ſhould ſee perfection; and ſayes thou, the fathers Kingdome before had perfect ſubjects, and ſo ſhall it have again when Chriſt hath perfected us; thou blinde guide, had the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> power to defile in this world? and hath not the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> power to cleanſe to the uttermoſt in this world what is defiled all that come to him? thou ſhoweſt thy ſelfe plainly whoſe power thou art under, none under the power of the Devil could ever witneſs the power of Chriſt; ſtop thy mouth thou falſe witneſs, we know the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt and the vertue of his reſurrection, and that he is greater in us than he that is in the world, &amp; that he is more able to ſave than the other to deſtroy, to cleanſe, than the other to defile; but while we believed with thee, we knew no more of it than thou doſt; but with that faith which overcomes the world and the devil, and purifies the heart, do we deny thee and thy faith, which lyes under ſin and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and in league with him for tearm of life, and would have all ſo too, and thou doſt what thou can to withſtand, that ever the Father ſhould have ſuch ſubjects again, as he had before the fall, never while the world ſtands: The laſt enemie (ſayes thou) is death, which ſhall then be overcome at the laſt reſurrection, a large time art thou taking for ſin and death to reigne, till all men be dead, thou art faithfull for thy God, and art making a league for him, with all that believe thee, even for them and their children after them, til there be not a man left to ſin any more, yet muſt not we ſay thou art in the Devils work, but we muſt call thee a Miniſter of righteouſneſs, though thou never read of ſuch a faith and Miniſtry in all the Scripture, but thou haſt in this thing plainly declared thou knows not the reſurrection nor fellowſhip of it, art who yet in <hi>death,</hi> and pleading for it, &amp; to compleat thy covenant of ſin, leaſt any ſhould deny it or break it, or ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t thee to be pleading for ſatan, thou concludes thy work with that old refuge
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118741:19"/>
of the devill, that is to take the Letter which was written to keep out of ſin, and to wreſt it to encourage to ſin, and thou runs to that one place which all thy Fathers children u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to plead, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1. If we ſay we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves; and the Truth is not in us, there fore ſayes thou, the truth is not in you quakers, I ſay <hi>Iohn</hi> was there ſhewing to little children, that there could be none free from ſin fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they was in Chriſt, not in ſelfe, nor while any thing of ſelf, remained, therefore ſayes, if we ſo think we deceive our ſelves, and though <hi>Iohn</hi> ſay (we) yet was it not his condition, but as he comes down to them to miniſter to their meaſures who was not yet cleanſed ſo he ſaith, (we) whereof he was not guilty, no more than <hi>Iames</hi> the Apoſtle was of curſing men with his Tongue, where he ſaith, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with bleſs we God, therewith curſe we men, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3 9. And many other places of Scripture, where they come down to the condition of the weak, yet partake of no mans ſin, though ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nclean beaſts as thee would take theſe Scriptures to plead for ſin ſo long as the world ſtands which <hi>Iohn</hi> wrote that they ſinned not; and thou concludes with this queſtion, if you think you are perfect without ſin, whether do you alſo think that you are already in heaven, or perfect glory; for what can keep the ſoul from perfect enjoyment of God but ſin, and to enjoy God perfectly, is to be glorified perfectly; but ſayeſt thou, I have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got that your brethren think heaven hell is onely with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n men; I ſay, hadſt thou forgot that lye, it had been an injury to him whom thou ſerves, but I find little of that forgetfulneſs in thy Book, and for perfect enjoyment of God, had not <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency perfect enjoyment of God? and Chriſt in his time when he was upon the earth, though their bodies was upon the earth, and ſo far as any is covered with Gods righteouſneſs, ſo far perfectly glorified, but tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren knows little of this, nor none that ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ought the honour and glory of this world, the prayers of ſuch was ever an abomination, and their profeſſion out of the ſaith of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 5. 44.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thou proceeds to ask more queries, and thou deſires me to ſpeak truly to the point in queſtion; I ſay, ſo I ſhall in plainneſs, paſſing by words to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>And firſt: Thou ſayes, are not they the very ſame MINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERS you raile at, which all the Drun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ards, Swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rers, Whoremongers, and ſenſuall wretches in the COUNTREY do hate and raile at? and are not ye on their ſide, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſses the ſame SPIRIT, would not all covetous MALIG<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ANIS have Tythes down as well as you; were not they of the ſame ſort of MINISTERS which the late BISHOPS ſilenced, is it not then the ſame SPIRIT, by which you are acted?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118741:20"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay railing we deny, and ſpeak the truth againſt thoſe we find out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, who are one with drunkards &amp; ſwearers, Whoremongers, and ſenſual wretches, and whoſe Church &amp; hearers is made up or many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch, and who by ſuch are upholden, maintained, and defended, who fight for ſuch a Miniſtry with clubs, and ſtones, and ſtocks, and theſe are of the ſame ſpirit with them and on their ſide, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſervants of God, beating in their Synagogues, and hailing out, as they ever did the miniſters of truth, who was ſent to preach the Goſpel, and bear witneſs againſt their falſe worſhips, whom they raged againſt with carnal weapons, as they had opportunity, and for hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng tythes down, they are ſo pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n againſt the practiſe of the ſaints, by you upholden, that they are blind that ſees it not, yea good and bad, except thoſe who have a gain by them; and I cannot blame the enemies o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God for wiſhing that down, which is contrary to God, and for Biſhops ſilenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, I ſay you are in the ſame work, and would ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all the appearance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God had you power, exceeding all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops herein, having perſecuted and impriſoned more in one yeares ſpace, than the Bishops did in ten; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or ſuch truthes declaring, as the Biſhops would have been ashamed to have impriſoned for, yea ſome of you Prieſts, proceeding to blood, with your own hands, being more exceedingly mad than ever your fathers was, who would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a law for that which they did, but you have none for many things you do, ſo you are acted by the ſame ſpirit, but exceedingly heightned in rage, more than ever they was.</p>
               <p>Thy ſecond Query is made up of a bundle of lyes, which I shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thee again from whence they came; as firſt: That we ſeduce the people from true teaching. 2 That we contemn the Scriptures. 3. That we prefer ſome Tranſlation or Language before another. 4. That we maintain free-wil before converſion. 5. Or deny it to be only the fruit of the Spirit in the Elect. 6. That we hold forth any for the fulfilling the commands of God, but Chriſt only in them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. 7. That we make our perfection only in caſting off worldly callings, relations, names, or any other thing, but in Chriſt himſelf, 8. or that thou haſt any thing under our hands that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith ſo. 9. That we place our righteouſneſs in our own works. 10. That we deny the imputed righteouſneſs of Chriſt. 11. That we (inſtead of preaching the righteouſneſs of Chriſt) we call out for our own formal righteouſneſs. 12. That our righteouſneſs conſiſts in any outward thing or places. 13. That we ſay no man may call maſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſtris any further than Chriſt fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds it, to the devils pride in proud men as phariſes, hirelings or the like. 14. That our righteouſneſs lyes in forbidding thoſe things. 15. That we are ignorant of Chriſts righteouſneſs. 16. That we take the moſt ſatannical lyes and ſlanders to be our righteouſneſs. 17. That the Papiſts and we conſpire together; Theſe ſeventeen devilliſh lyes haſt thou laid upon us, yet if we ſo call them the father of them is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, though we have no other name for them by the Spirit of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118741:20"/>
God, which comes not to cover the lyar, but to lay him open, nor gild his works with a fine name; and thou ſayes thou could tel many more were it not too tedious, but if thou undertake in plainneſs to prove but one of theſe, thou haſt telled it wil be more tedious than they are all in telling; and for the Papiſts denying your Miniſtry, or confeſſing the ſufficiency of the Light of Chriſt, or witneſſing freedome from ſin in him, wherein (by thy confeſſion) they come nearer to the truth in words than you do, though as far off in practiſe; I ſay, ſhall we deny the Truth becauſe they profeſs it? or the light of Chriſt and his redemption becauſe they profeſs it in words? I ſay nay, nor doth this prove us of the ſame Spirit with them, for it is the fruits that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts the Spirit, and not words; and by that we deny both the Papiſts and you, and all that ſay and do not, and wherein you ſay the truth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 23 3.</note> that we obſerve, but do not as you do, and ſo to the point, the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is anſwered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quest.</hi> 3. Whether there were ever greater Monſters of ingratitude than theſe are? who ſet their hearts and tongues againſt the Miniſters of Chriſt, that lay out themſelves for ſaving of Souls, through all the ſcorn and oppoſition of all ſorts of wicked men, with whom theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches joyn againſt them, yea and make their very ſtudy and labour their crime, when it were much eaſier for us to preach without ſtudy, and that I hope with ſomewhat more truth, ſenſe, and order, then they that ſo boaſt of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſum of this query hath been formerly anſwered, that you are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, neither do abide in his Doctrine, but are thoſe with whom theſe wretches they ſpeak of joyne both in your worſhip, and to uphold you, and that Miniſtry which abides not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, is not for ſaving of Souls, nor do we make your ſtudy your crime, but your whole worſhip, which by the Doctrine of Chriſt we deny, and for thy more ſenſe and order which thou boaſteſt on, then we that boaſt of the Spirit, I ſay we have nothing elſe to boaſt on but that Spirit that was alwayes counted madneſs and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thy generation, and thats the Spirit of Truth, which with thy ſenſe and ſenſuall wiſdome thou reproacheſt, and this is the end of thy ſtudy, as appears in thy paper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 4. Were not theſe faithfull ſervants of God that ſuffered mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome under heathen and Arian perſecutors, juſt ſuch Miniſters as theſe men vill fie? or wherein was the difference, and do not theſe wretches juſtifie their murders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay no; nor like them, no more than the ſufferer is like the perſecutor, and therein was the difference and is the difference, they ſuffered in obedience to that meaſure of light in their times, and we ſuffer in obedience to the light of Chriſt in theſe times, they ſuffered by the chiefe Prieſts in their times, who had got power from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; and we ſuffer by the chiefe Prieſts who have got power from the Magiſtrate, and it is not the name of Pope, Biſhop, or Prieſt, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118741:21"/>
makes juſt ſuch, or not ſuch, but the practiſe wherein they are found, and ſuch are the ſervants of God, who are found in the work of God, &amp; ſuch are the ſervants of the Devil, who are found perſecutors then, and now juſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying their murders, who then acted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu,</hi> 5. Are not the Miniſters who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe men deſpiſe, of the ſame calling practiſe as thoſe were that ſuffered death in the flames in queen <hi>Maryes</hi> dayes, ſuch as <hi>Brad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er, Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ley, Cranmore, Saunders, Philpot,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, were not theſe called Maſters, did they not preach in pulpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and take tythes or money for preaching, as their due maintenance, and the other things that the quake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s accuſe us for, and do not theſe men juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie the bloody oppoſers of them, and condemns Gods Saints afre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> I ſay it was for denying of that which was the Popiſh way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip, according to their meaſure of Light, that theſe men then ſuffered, and being faithful to that meaſure they were excepted, though the fulneſs of the Light was not then come, but this is no ground to uphold the reſt of their Popiſh inventions contrary to Goſpel wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and if they thus fared, who did but witneſs againſt ſome bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, what may we expect, who holds forth that light which ſtrikes at the Root? therefore we think it not ſtrange to ſee your rage greater, if you had power, then theirs was, and it is you that juſtifies the bloody oppoſers, and condemns the Saints afreſh, as may be ſeen in the Goals of the Nation, whom you have impriſoned, not having yet an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity for blood, and here you are found in the practiſe that the popiſh Prieſts was in, perſecuting and not ſuffering.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 6. Whether ever the earth bore men that did more proudly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe others in compariſon of themſelves, and whether their language ſavour of the Spirit of the Lamb of God, or can he have any taſt of that Spirit of Chriſt in himſelf, that doth not even feel that their proud and railing language is of the Devil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Proud &amp; deſpiteful compariſons we deny, &amp; find thee in that nature in thy 3. <hi>qu.</hi> Wherein thou ſays, without ſtudy thou canſt preach more ſenſe and order, than we that boaſt of the Spirit, where thou compares thy ſenſe with the ſpirit, and boaſts above it, neither canſt thou charge us with any language, but what the Lamb uſed, and thoſe that was guided by him, and thou that calls that railing and the Language of the Devill, haſt no taſt of the Spirit of Chriſt in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 7. Was there ever a Generation known on the earth, that did more arrogantly ſtep up into the Throne of God, and ſenſure his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, whoſe faces they never ſaw, and who they can charge with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but being Preache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the Goſpel, and that in a Pulpet, having an hour-glaſs, taking tythes, &amp;c. to be Miniſters of the Devil, ſons or Perdition, with much of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke, though Chriſt hath ſaid, judge not left ye be judged, and who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant to his own Maſter he ſtands or falls.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118741:21"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This Query is wholly made up of deceit, for they are not the<note place="margin">2 Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> preachers of the Goſpel whom we charge; neither in power nor form, but out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and the practiſe of his Miniſters, both in maintenance and manner of worſhip, who preach in pulpets with hour-glaſſes, and take tythes, &amp;c. and finding them out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and practiſe of his Miniſters, they are declared to be the Miniſters of Antichriſt, and no Servants of Chriſt, and ſo they are judged, and Chriſt never ſaid judge not ſuch, but preſcribed a rule whereby we ſhould judg them, even by their fruits ye ſhal know them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo to thy maſter thou art fallen, and to him thou ſtands pleading fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his kingdome, and in this fruit I finde thee and know thee, and with the Spirit of Chriſt I judge thee, though thy face I never ſee, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> generation that ever judged ſuch, was never known to the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though they walked on the earth, and by the earth ſuffered, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is arrogancy that ſteps up into the Throne of God, and perſecutes h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſervants.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 8. Was there ever a Generation of men on whom the image <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Devill was more viſible then on theſe, he is the Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Pride, and Malice, and the depth of ignorance and height of pride and malice breaks out ſo aboundantly in their carriage and diſcourſe, that all that are not utterly blind may ſee it, it is the work of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil to be an accuſer of the Brethren, and ſo it is the very religion and buſineſs of theſe wretches, to accuſe Miniſters &amp; godly people to be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite lyars, children of the devil, Serpents, vipers, with much the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> There was a generation of men wherin the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage of the devil was the Prince of darkneſs, &amp; theſe was they that denyed the light of Chriſt to be ſufficient, were proud and covetous, laid heavy burdens on the people, ſaid and did not, profeſſed God, but brought forth the works of the Devil, and the depth of their ignorance, and height of pride brake out ſo aboundantly in their practiſe, that all that were not utterly blind might ſee it, and it was the practiſe of Chriſt and his Miniſters to declare theſe openly to be hypocrites, lyars, children of the devill, ſerpents, vipers, and much the like; and they did not herein accuſe the brethren nor Godly Miniſters, nor godly people, but ſuch as wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked contrary to God, and to ſpeak the ſame words to the ſame genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are found in the ſame works by the ſame ſpirit, is the ſame to God, as it was then, and the ſame to that generation, who are found in their works, if not, prove thou when it was changed, elſe thou art the accuſer of the brethren, and that falſly.</p>
               <p>qu. 9. Is it no kinde of blaſphemy of the Holy Ghoſt, for ſuch WRETCHES, when they have powred out the moſt horrid LYES, SLANDERS, RAILINGS and falſe Doctrines to profeſs ſolemnly that all this is from the Spirit
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118741:22"/>
of Chriſt within them, and make God and his holy Spirit the pater of all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be found in the ſame practiſe that Chriſt and his Miniſters<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 44.</note> was found in, bearing witneſs againſt the ſame things is no railing, ſlandring, nor no falſe Doctrine, being done from the Spirit of Chriſt within them, is no blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt, but obedience to it; and in thee, who knows not Gods holy Spirit to be the author and patern of all, thy author and patern is the Devil, where God is not the Author and Father, the works begotten and brought forth by him, ſuch are of your father the devill, and his works you do, this is that Spirit I told thee of before, who denies God to be thy author and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, the author and fini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her of our faith and works, ſo muſt we needs be contrary the one to the other, both in judgment and practiſe, as far a Chriſt and <hi>Belial,</hi> as in our meaſures we have received him who is the faithfull witneſs in all Generations, againſt thoſe wayes you now live in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 10. Can that man that hath one ſpark of Grace, believe that he hath no ſin? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay by grace we are ſaved, which we have received of God which teacheth us to ſpeak the truth, by which truth we are ſet free, ſo far as we know him, and ſo far we declare our freedome, according<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 10.</note> to our meaſures, and he that ſees himſelfe ſet free from all ſin by that<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20.</note> power, and brought wholly unto Chriſt, where there is no ſin, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhame,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iob.</hi> 8. 5, 6.</note> the body of ſin put off, and nothing living in him but the life of Chriſt, if he declare this to his praiſe, he is no lyar, and if ſuch an one abide in Chriſt, he ſinneth not, neither doth ſuch an one ſay he hath no knowledg of Chriſt, nor need of the Phyſician, nor that he wil not be beholding to him for his blood, or to make interceſſion, neither doth he deny that he hath ſinned, but confeſſes to his praiſe who hath him cleanſed according to his meaſure, nor is this to ſay he wil not be beholding to God any more, who ſtands by faith in his power, and is beholding to him daylie, and to his blood dayly, which as it hath wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſo keeps pure from horrid railing, ſlandering, and other wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thy ſwearing, and drinking thou ſpeaks on; and this is to confeſs Chriſt come in the fleſh, the juſt man on the earth that doth good and ſins not, who is greater then <hi>Solomon,</hi> and ſuch deny the Phariſees and Papiſts, and all that juſtifie themſelves are Lyars, before him, and to<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 19.</note> him <hi>Solomon</hi> confeſſed; though the Law made not perfect, yet he doth all that come to him, and ſo preſents them to the father, and this is<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 19.</note> our ſtandart againſt the enemy that would overflow us, which the hireling knows not, whoſe the ſheep are not, nor their paſture, who are not wretched, nor under the power of the deceiver, which things thou would charge upon us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 11. Whether thoſe that deny Scripture to be Gods Word, as theſe quakers do, and deny that there is any ſuch perſon as Jeſus Chriſt which ſuffered at Jeruſalem, now glorified in Heaven, in the humane
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118741:22"/>
nature, and only cals ſomwhat that is within themſelves, by the name of Chriſt; I ſay, whether are not theſe abominable infidells, having nothing to do with the name of Chriſtians?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That we deny the perſon of Jeſus who ſuffered at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> now glorified in Heaven in his body, is a lying ſlander, but thou that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies God to be the word, and ſayes the Letter is the Word, art igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant both of the word and Scriptures, as plainly they ſhall witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt thee, which ſayes, <hi>God is the word,</hi> and the word of God is the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.</note> Name of Ieſus, as the Scripture declareth, but never takes that name<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 11.</note> to its ſelfe; <hi>And the word of God endures for ever:</hi> and this is the word<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 25.</note> which by the Goſpel is preached, which is not the Letter; and thou that knoweſt not the Letter within thee, art the Infidel and Reprobate<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</note> thou ſpeaks on, who hath nothing to do with the name of a Chriſtian, who art adding thy lyes and ſlanders, as though only we limited Chriſt within us, becauſe we witneſs him in us, ſo with the Scripture thou art proved to be ignorant of them, and the power of God; from which they were written.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 12. Is it not damnable hypocriſie in the wretches to prate ſo much of Scripture, and call for Scripture, while they thus deny it to be Gods word?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> In this query thou ſhews thy confuſion, one while charging us to prate too much of Scriptures, and call for Scriptures, and yet thy end is to make people believe that we deny Scriptures becauſe we will not own the Scriptures by the name of Chriſt, who is called the word of God, and in thy ſeeking occaſion to ſlander, but can finde none; thou ſhews thy damnable hypocriſie and wretchedneſs, &amp; denies both the Word and Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>que.</hi> 13. Is it not damnable hypocriſie in them to call themſelves Chriſtians, when they are infidells, and deny the perſon of Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified to be in Heaven?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is damnable hypocriſie and wickedneſs for thee to continue thylying, ſaying that we deny the perſon of Chriſt cruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fied to be in<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5.</note> Heaven, and thou thy ſelf art the infidell, who cannot believe Jeſus Chriſt in the Saints, but calls it a thing within us, but canſt not own it by the name of Chriſt, as in thy 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> query, and that faith is Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. 10.</note> and thou that knows not Chriſt in thee art the Infidell, for he that believes hath the witneſs in himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 14. Is not he a Pagan and no chriſtian, that thinks that the Light which is in all the Indians, Americans, and other Pagans on earth, is ſufficient without Scripture?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay that Light which the Gentiles had, which brought them to do the things contained in the Law, ſhowing the work of the Law<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> written intheir hearts, was ſufficient without the circumciſion of the Letter, which the Jews ſtood ſo much on, yet brought not forth the ſame fruits which God accepted, though they could call them Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Gentiles, as thou doſt the Indians and Pagans, but it the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118741:23"/>
Indeans and Pagans own that Law written in their heart, and come to receive power to bring forth the fruits of it, which thou doſt not; I ſhall ſay of you both as <hi>Paul</hi> did of the Jews, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not the hearers of the Law are juſt before God, but the doers of the Law ſhall be juſtified; but art not thou a Pagan, if not worſe, who would conclude all in condemnation, but who comes to hear you hirelings, and your expoſitions of the Scriptures? nay thou art a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, above all thou readeſt on in the ſcripture, who would make the light of Chriſt (wherewith he hath enlightned every one that comes into the world) to be inſufficient without ſcripture, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all the Saints and their ſufficiency, before the Letter was, and ſo<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> deſtroy <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith and ſufficiency, which had no Letter to add to it, but this is all thou knows of it or its foundation, who denies its ſufficiency.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 15. Was that Light in <hi>Paul</hi> which perſwaded him that he ought to do many things againſt the name of Jeſus, ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him to the faith of Jeſus? or did Chriſt give him needleſly a light from heaven, and by <hi>Ananias</hi> his Doctrine? or had <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſufficient Light within him before <hi>Peter</hi> preached unto him? or had all the world ſufficient Light within them, before Chriſt ſent abroad his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to preach the Goſpel unto them? or did Chriſt ſend them a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs light by his Apoſtles? have thoſe perſecutors ſufficient light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them to cauſe them to believe in Chriſt, who think they do God ſervice in killing or reproaching his miniſters and people?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſay Chriſt hath enlightned every one that comes into the World, which <hi>Ball,</hi> and thou, and many of thy generation, being exceedingly mad, with envy and rage, running in your own wills, and acting againſt it, your light is become Darkneſs, and ſo great is that darkneſs, that you are reproaching, perſecuting, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the people of God now, as he was then, and think you do God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, yet is the Light in Darkneſs, though Darkneſs comprehends it not;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> 1. 5.</note> and therefore <hi>Peter</hi> was ſent to <hi>Cornelius, Ananias,</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Apoſtles to the world, not to give them eyes, but to open the blinde eyes, and to turn them from Darkneſs to the Light, as is plain, Chriſt and the Apoſtles came into the world for that purpoſe, though Chriſt was the light before the world was, yet came into the world to open the eyes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46 6, 7. and ſent his Apoſtles to that end, at is plaine <hi>Act.</hi> 26. i7, i8 and to the <hi>Light</hi> that ſhun in Darkneſs was they to turn<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19.</note> them, and this was the way by which they knew God, to which they confeſſed, as is plain in the Stripture, til which time the Goſpel was hid, and the CREATURE loſt by reaſon of that DARK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS, wherewith the Prince of this World had their hearts blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3. to the 8. ver. and this Light did not perſwade <hi>Paul</hi> to be a perſecuter, nor thee neither, but the Prince of Darkneſs which hath thee blinded, wherein thou appears to be one of thoſe builders
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118741:23"/>
who refuſes the Corner Stone, and denies Gods covenant, which<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 6.</note> was a covenant of Light, and not of the Letter, and the Law written in the heart, and not in the Tables, which the carnall eye ſees not, nor<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 23. 26</note> thy wilfull minde regards not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who art crying, lo here, lo there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, but ſaith Chriſt, go not forth, the word is nigh thee in thy<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 8.</note> heart, and that word of faith the Apoſtles preached, which was in peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts, but ſuch was not Miniſters of the Letter but of the Spirit, nor did ever ſay the Letter was the Word, as thou doſt, but if the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be not the Word, it ſeems thou hath none of the Word, but art one of thoſe who ſaith, hear the word of the Lord, when the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.</note> Lord never ſpoke to thee, but hath ſtoln it from thy neighbor which is none of the word of the Lord to thee, ſo thou perverts it, taking the Scriptures to plead for ſin which was written againſt ſin, which they that had the word of the Lord never did, and that Light which thou denieſt to us, is become the head of the corner, and we witneſs it ſufficient without any other addittion, but thy teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it is the teſtimony of an unbeliever, contrary to what Chriſt commandeth, thereby to be become the children of light; there is the covenant and the promiſe of it, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12. 36. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 12. and out of the Light, theres no promiſe, and all that thou haſt here proved is but thy ſelf a child of Darkneſs, and no otherwayes to be believed, ſo brings forth thy deeds of Darkneſs, ſpeaking evil of that thou knoweſt not, and none can own <hi>Ananias</hi> Doctrine<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 10. 11.</note> who denies immediate callings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 16. If all have ſufficient Light within them, what need you go up and down to perſwade them, is it needleſs Light that you bring them, or is it helliſh darkneſs?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> We are ſent to declare that Light which is ſufficient, which we witneſs within us, and to draw people from that helliſh darkneſs into which the blinde guides have led them, and from all the dark worſhipps ſet up in the imaginations unto the light of life, which is only ſufficient; which bears witneſs in them againſt all the Deeds of Darknes, ſhowing what is to be reproved and what is wrought in God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 13. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 21. ſo to turn people<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. 13.</note> to that Light and Spirit of Truth, which leads into all Truth, is the end of our Teaching, and the enemy of helliſh Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that Spirit is in them, and they ſhall know it who turn to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 17. Is it not a moſt ſottiſh trick of you to go up and down prating and commanding, and yet refuſe to ſhew your commiſſion <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>from God, and to call Miniſters to ſhew theirs and refuſe to ſhew your own, but ſay it is inviſible within you, are you ſo mad to expect that any ſhould believe an inviſible and indemonſtrable COMMISSION, and might not we as wel
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118741:24"/>
we tel you ours is inviſible, but that indeed it is not, or ſhould we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve every one that prates of a commiſſion within him or no? if not, why ſhould we believe you more than others that ſay the like?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Our call and commiſſion is inviſible as to you, as ever it was to the world, yet herein is it ſhewed that we are found in the ſame practiſe and ſuffering, that all the Saints of God ever was, for decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the falſe worſhips, and this we refuſe not to ſhow in the midſt of your envy, in the patience of Chriſt and his long ſuffering, in the midſt of your bloody perſecution, and here is your commiſſion ſhewed alſo, and from whom you have it, even him that is within you who is known by his fruits outward, a murderer from the beginning ſo is the Spirit of God by its fruits outward, a ſufferer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo each tree is known by its fruit, whatſoever you tel us, and thats the ſot which cannot ſee it nor believe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 18. Seeing you cry down our Miniſtry and Churches, tell us which is the the true miniſtry and Church, and when yours begun? and where it hath been ſince Chriſts abode on earth til now? ſpeak plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and let us know, whether you indeed are Papiſts or Pagans?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The true Miniſtry and Church is thoſe who abide in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, guided by his Spirit, in the way of his worſhip, and this Church begun to be ſeperated from the world, firſt in <hi>Abell,</hi> and ſince Chriſts abode on the earth hath been thruſt into corners, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and impriſoned, and killed by <hi>Cains</hi> generation, who was ever worſhippers yet in their murderous nature, and here we ſpeak plainly ſuch was Pagans and Papiſts, though they called themſelves Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, the ſame are you now, who are found in the ſame works, though you call your ſelves chriſtians, and ſuch churches we cry down, and their miniſtry, who hath their hands in blood and perſecution, whatſoever they are called by; and now that we have ſpoken plainly and truth alſo, ſee thou be not angry and call trailing, and plot miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe againſt us in ſecret, as your father <hi>Cain</hi> did and all his genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when you cannot do it openly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 19. Is not that man an infidel and a ſcorner of Chriſt that dare ſay he came into the world and ſhed his blood to gather onely a few raging quakers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n England. 1652 years after his incarnat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, if Chriſt have no ſubjects but theſe, he is a poore King; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Chriſt have been t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll now without ſubjects, he was no King, if without a Body, he was no Head, if without a ſpouſe, he was no husband; Therefore ſhew us what a church Chriſt had, or confeſs your ſelves infidels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The neareſt compariſon as I finde in Scripture whereby to ſhew what a Church Chriſt had, ſince the myſtery of iniquity, and Popiſh Prieſthood, and Pariſh Maſters, was ſet up in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ailing away, may be compared to his Church, from the time that the hirelings and falſe Prophets begun amongſt the Jews to preach for hire, and bear rule by their means, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> even til Chriſts comming in the fleſh, which Church was ſometimes viſible, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a few d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpiſed Prophets, who were ſent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118741:24"/>
one after another, to cry down the falſe worſhips &amp; covetous practiſes, and to teſtifie of his comming, which alwai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red by the multitude o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prieſts and ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Prophets, who when they came ſtil conſpired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and if thou look back ſince your lordly authority was ſet up in your Miniſtry, you may ſee they have had their hands in the like practiſe againſt thoſe who lived in hope of his appearance, denying their worſhips, and now it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alne into your hands, who are garniſhing their Sepulchers, crying out againſt your fathers, the Popes, and the Biſhops, for their cruelty, but are found deeper in it to your power than ever they was, ſcarcely ever ceaſing to ſtir any authority of the nation againſt the Lamb, and his Light where it is made manifeſt; yea many of your Generation not finding the Magiſtrate ſo ready to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute your bloody deſignes, as you would have them, have ſhed blood with your own hands, even of the innocent, and they are not a few that are guilty hereof, in the north parts of this Nation, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt hath been poore according to thy judgement, yet hath theſe been his ſubjects; nor hath he been without a body, nor without a ſpouſe, ſo thou mayeſt read what a Church Chriſt hath, and what a Church he hath had formerly, yet is he not come to ſave a few raging quakers only, but with ten thouſand of his ſaints is he come to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of that bloody Generation: and for the Infidell thou tells on, and the ſcorner of Chriſt, that is he that cannot believe in him, and his Light to be ſufficient: and what a church Chriſt hath had and hath, we have ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>qu.</hi> 20. Did not the ſpirit of the Quakers ſpeak in numbers 16. 3. juſt as you do now againſt magiſtrates, and miniſters, and is not God very patient that cauſeth not the earth to open and ſwallow you up quick, as it did them? do you underſtand that the <hi>Simonians</hi> (or diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) and the <hi>Nicholaitans,</hi> whoſe Doctrine and deeds Chriſt hateth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. and other gnoſtick heriticks in the Apoſtles dayes did deal by them and the Church then as you do by us now; and that the ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>Peter,</hi> the Epiſtle of <hi>Iude,</hi> much of the firſt of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the ſecond of <hi>Iohn,</hi> were written purpoſely againſt them, beſides many other Scriptures, and have you wel conſidered thoſe Scriptures, and applyed them to your ſelves?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That Spirit of Chriſt we own, is that meek Spirit that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was in <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt which the Rebellious Levites was then gathered, who would condemn it of too much purity, ſaying that all the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was holy, the ſame which you do now, calling all Chriſtians, and ſprinkl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng their Children under the name of believers, and that Spirit which we own, ſpeaks not againſt Magiſtracy nor Miniſtry, ſuch as are appointed by God, though it hath ever teſtified againſt the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Magiſtracy which by God was appointed, yet canſt not thou here ſhelter thy ſelfe, who art out of the Doctrine of Chriſt in all thy Miniſtry, and was never called by him, and thy ſpirit we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to be worſe than <hi>Simon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Magus,</hi> for he believed in the Light of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118741:25"/>
the Goſpel, but thou denyeſt it, and he would have bought the gift which thou would ſel if thou hadſt it, neither had he a hand in ſuch works of envy againſt the Truth, as thou and thy generation are found in, though there then was heriticks, who dealt with the Apoſtlesthen, as you do with us now, and thoſe was and are the heriticks who abides not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, who are proud and covetous, cannot ceaſe from ſin, have hearts exerciſed in wicked practiſes, after <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Balaam,</hi> and of theſe did <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeak of in their Epiſtles,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 2, 3</note> and <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo, who declared that then Antichriſt was gone into the<note place="margin">i <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. 9, i0.</note> World, and that was the Spirit of Antichriſt who denyed Chriſt in them, but they that believe hath the witneſs in themſelves, and they that abode not in the Doctrine of Chriſt, and had the Father and<note place="margin">2 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. 10,</note> the Son, they was not to receive them into their houſes, neither bid them God ſpeed, and wouldſt thou be found in theſe practiſes, and have us to apply theſe Scriptures to us, who deny thoſe practiſes; thou canſt not hide thy ſelf here, when thou finds us in thoſe things, apply thou thoſe Scriptures unto us; in the mean time, take thy portion from them, being condemned by them, and we have conſidered thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and finde them written againſt thy generation and your practiſe and ſo we apply them unto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:118741:25"/>
               <head>And for the clearer manifeſting what Goſpel and faith thou Preaches, I ſhall lay down theſe queries following, they being that which every true Miniſter knows, and very needful to be known to all people.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, Hath the firſt Adam power upon earth to defile all that are in him, and hath not the ſecond as much power and vertue to cleanſe from all ſin all that are in him? if ſo, then what is the cauſe men muſt commit ſin and be imperfect while they live in this world?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether is that new birth ſpoken on (without which none can be ſaved) Chriſt formed in believers, or only a believing that he was manifeſt in the fleſh, 1655<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> years ſince, and hath not the Devil and reprobates this beliefe latter mentioned.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hath any life eternal in them, but who hath the fleſh and blood of Chriſt in them? and is life eternal known any other way ſavingly in this world while people live?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is any the Sons of God further then they are guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in all things? and is not the Spirit of God a ſufficient guide to all who have it in all things, without any other help according to the meaſure received.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether the Spirit of God in them who have it (according to its meaſure) be not the abſolute Judge of all Spirits, the opener of all Scriptures? and whether needs it any viſible thing to add to it, or can any other thing judge it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether can any other Spirits judge of Scripture, or any of the works of God aright, but wreſts Scripture to the deſtruction of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and calls light darkneſs, and darkneſs light, and can any other ſpirit judg according to God in any thing?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether the Word of God can be changed, or can it admit of ſeverall meanings, as to one particular thing? is it viſible or inviſible, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r is there any word but one, and whether was that word before the letter, and ſhall be when the letter is turned to duſt?</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:118741:26"/>8. Whether is the leaſt meaſure of ſaving faith preſent power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the greateſt power of darkneſs, and able to keep out of all ſin whatſoever, if the creature abide in it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether ever any Miniſter of Chriſt had any hand in impriſoning any man for coming into their meeting places; or was any beat in the meeting places where a Miniſter of Chriſt was preacher, and was it not the manner of the Apoſtles to reaſon and diſpute in the Synagogues againſt their falſe worſhip, and was not all perſecutors and fighters againſt God, who oppoſed them, and is it not the ſame now where the ſame Spirits are, and is that the Spirit of God or of the Devil which ſayes its no more perſecution to put ſuch in priſon, than to burn a thiefe in the hand, as thou doſt?</p>
               <p n="10">10. Where that temple of God is where the man of ſins ſits, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf that he is God, and muſt not the Light of Iſrael reveale him firſt where he is, and then binde him and caſt him out, and when he is caſt out, whether is not the body of ſin wholly put off, yea or nay? or can he return in again unleſs the creatures mind go out to his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations firſt, and do not ſuch depart out of the covenant of life and faith, and ſo make ſhipwrack of the good conſcience?</p>
               <p n="11">11. Whether is the light of Chriſt Spirituall, or can it be known any other way but in Spirit within, and is not the light of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the abſolute way out of death and darkneſs, or doth it ſtand need of any temporall thing to help it to enlighten thoſe who are turned to it, believe in it and love it?</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whether is the Goſpel Miniſtry the ſame it was in the Apoſtles times, both for matter and manner, means and maintenance? if nor, when was it changed (and by whom) into Steeplehouſes, Tythes and great Parſonages, and that order of worſhip now uſed, ſeeing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you are erred out of the way of the Apoſtles in every particular of your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Whether may not the Spirit of God (in whom it is) uſe the ſame words againſt falſe teachers now, as it former hath done againſt them that was found in the ſame practiſe? and is there any plainer tryall of theſe two Spirits in this world the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by their fruits herein, as is found in Scripture; and is it now any more railing and bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emy than it was then, or by what name m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t a lye be called according to Scripture and the practiſe of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118741:26"/>Theſe queries I have not put forth to keep up ſtrife, but being things much contended about with many, if thou in plainneſs give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy faith herein, the difference may be known betwixt us and you Prieſts, Teachers, and whether of us owns the Saints practiſe as is declared in Scripture<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but if thou fold them up by ſix together, and ſend us to a book to ſeek an anſwer we know not where, as thou d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dſt in thy laſt book, or if thou anſwer them with ſleighting and ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling when thou come to the Thing intended, as thou haſt done, thou wilt be ſeen, and thy cover wil diſcover thee to all the children of light.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
